<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Liberty of conscience: or The sole means to obtaine peace and truth. Not onely reconciling His Majesty with His subjects, but all Christian states and princes to one another, with the freest passage for the gospel. Very seasonable and necessary in these distracted times, when most men are weary of war, and cannot finde the way to peace.</title>
            <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1675</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E39_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20544</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864820</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864820</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 7:E39[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Liberty of conscience: or The sole means to obtaine peace and truth. Not onely reconciling His Majesty with His subjects, but all Christian states and princes to one another, with the freest passage for the gospel. Very seasonable and necessary in these distracted times, when most men are weary of war, and cannot finde the way to peace.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Robinson. Sometimes attributed to William Walwyn; this attribution rejected by McMichael and Taft, The writings of William Walwyn, p.528.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 24th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LIBERTY OF CONSCIENCE: OR THE Sole means to obtaine <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not onely reconciling His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> with His Subjects, but all Chriſtian States and Princes to one another, with the freeſt paſſage for the GOSPEL.</p>
            <p>Very ſeaſonable and neceſſary in theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted times, when moſt men are weary of War, and cannot finde the way to Peace.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117052:2"/>
            <head>To every Chriſtian Reader that ſeeks Truth as well as Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved in Chriſt Jeſus:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LEt not the ſeeming noveltie of opinions deter thee from ſearching out the Truth, and be aſſured that Gods people, as well as world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings have their times to fiſh in troubled waters; wherefore before thou proceed on with this Diſcourſe, promiſe me, I beſeech thee, to read it out; and if thou then repent thee of thy paines, let me but know ſo much, and I ſhall willingly take upon me a double penance for thy ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and amends.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that the lawfulneſſe of newtrality is much controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both in policie and conſcience, but men of moderation which endeavour to qualifie or decline the precipice of extreams, ought not to be accounted newtralls or luke-warme: Such then (as I preſume) will no more be of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that all on the Kings ſide are Papiſts or Popiſhly affected, then that all on the Parliaments are Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, or thereunto inclined; nor all that are at <hi>Oxford</hi> enemies of God and godly men, or all at <hi>London</hi> to take up Arms only for good of either; but that there are on both ſides great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, though not equall, which wiſh ſincerely and mean well, not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there may have been many weakneſſes, infirmities &amp; errours expreſſed by them; for, the preſence and influence of both the Armies I conceive but much alike conducing to make the people really good or bad, though they muſt outwardly comply with both, ſo long as they are neare them, and have any thing to loſe, and do not yet perceive, but that ſuch Members of the Lords and Commons Houſe, are much the ſame, notwithſtanding their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to and fro between <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>London</hi> Pamphlets querie, whether Papiſts are likely to ſettle the Proteſtant Religion? And <hi>Aulicus</hi> ſeeming no leſſe ſcrupulous, askes whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Browniſts or Anabaptiſts will? But if a third ſhould reſolve them both, and ſay, that the Proteſtant Religion hath not been in <hi>England</hi> theſe eighty years, he might run the hazard to be thought a libeller, and yet it may chance be found ſo, if we examine what it is, whence it came, whether it be not confined amongſt the Lutherans, and how much we differ from it, though we ſtill retain the name: But what matters it, whether we be called Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants or otherwiſe? or is truth and propriety the worſe, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, or attaine them by the helpe of Papiſts and of Brownists? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not Papiſts and Browniſts as lawfully ſerve their King and Countrey, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thundering legions of Primitive Chriſtians did the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> The King ſaies he took up defenſive Arms; and both Houſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a verre that they did ſo: The Parliament party fear that if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough his Majeſty himſelfe be not Popiſhly affected, the Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by their juriſdiction, ſuppreſſe all ſuch as did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> both to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſcipline and doctrine: On the other ſide, the Kings party is
<pb facs="tcp:117052:2"/>
in as great a fear, that if the Parliaments ſide ſhould get the upper hand, though they do not eſtabliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or Anabaptiſme, yet they would ſettle a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, which may as much a bridge them the Liberty of Conſcience, as they themſelves have been a bridged under Epiſcopacie heretofore; in which reſpect, each party for the preſent, pretends to grant ſuch a liberty as ſhall be ſutable and complying with tender conſciences, but neither dare yeeld unto, or truſt the other: In ſuch a caſe as this, is there no remedy? Hath God left us quite deſtitute of meanes to ſtop ſo great a gap to prevent the totall ruine and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of three Nations, not without the greateſt ſcandall and offence which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver befell the Reformed Proteſtant Religion? The feare is equall and extream on both ſides, though either of them is like enough to ſay, the others fear is but imaginary, yet both of them, ſince they ſay ſo, and cannot be diſproved, are to be treated and proceeded with, alike: To this the King addes, and ſaies, that beſides ſundry demonſtrations of His grace and favour, I have granted <hi>a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Parliament,</hi> and if ever that ſhould have an end, they have ſtill <hi>a trieniall Parliament to perpetuity,</hi> which of themſelves only tranſcend all the grants that ever my Predeceſſours made unto their Subjects: and notwithſtanding all this, they attempt my life, and take away my Revenues, Royalty, and Religion too, if it were poſſible: On the contrary, the two Houſes of Parliament in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Remonſtrances have informed his Majeſty, how through predominancie of evill counſellours the Subjects liberties have had ſeverall great breaches made upon them, innovations of Doctrine and Diſcipline in their Religion, and they are really and totally poſſeſſed, that by the ſame, and ſuch like evill counſellours which are likely to ſucceed, their whole priviledges and propriety will be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from them, and the profeſſion of the true Proteſtant Religion utterly abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; aſſuring his Majeſty notwithſtanding, that if he will be pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto his great Councell, cauſe delinquents to be brought to triall, and ſettle the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome in ſuch perſons as both Houſes may confide in, there ſhall be no failing on their parts to make him <hi>a glorious Prince, beloved at home, feared abroad, and enlarge his Revenues beyond all his Predeceſſours;</hi> but not finding how to qualifie the diffidence which each hath of the other, both ſides have ſtrengthned themſelves, brought ſeverall Armies into the field, fought ſome pitcht battells, and had ſo many skirmiſhes and encounters, as, beſides the firing of whole Townes, deflouring of Virgins, committing rapes, rapines, and a thouſand other villanies, hath been the death perhaps of above a hundred thouſand ſoules in <hi>England</hi> only, then which, what could poſſibly befall more offenſive unto God; or damageable to the State? Surely both parties ſhould be deſirous of compoſing ſuch a difference, which in ſo high a nature and degree, is totally deſtructive unto both? But alas! the jealouſies are ſuch, that neither dare well offer, or entertain a Treaty, leſt the other ſhould make advantage of it; &amp; yet a King cannot be ſaid to deal too great a meaſure of love unto his people, nor ſubjects to out-doe their duty unto their King; nor the ſword be ſaid or thought properly or juſtly to have a capacity and power of ſettling true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of all ranks and conditions whatſoever, more glorifie the King
<pb facs="tcp:117052:3"/>
of Kings, then in renouncing all earthly intereſts and advantages, rather then his great Name ſhould be evill ſpoken of, or the bloud of his deareſt Saints to be ſpilt upon the ground, and yet we cannot poſſibly imagine, without the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſcandall of our owne charity, and offence unto the weaker brethren, but that ſome of them have already dyed on either ſide, God of his infinite mercy direct them both, that neither of them come ſhort or be found guilty in either.</p>
            <p>Another of the <hi>London</hi> queries is, Whether if Religion, and the Stat ebe in imminent danger of an <hi>Oxford</hi> party, both Houſes of Parliament, and ſo great a portion as adheres unto them, may not defend themſelves by Armes? and ſince <hi>Aulicus</hi> ſeems to be as much afraid that both Religion, Laws, and Priviledges of Parliament are equally endangered by the <hi>London</hi> Apprentices, and thoſe that went to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> ſome will thinke it beſt to anſwer both in one, and ſay, neceſſity hath no law, it is above all law, and though there be neither Act of Parliament, Ordinance of both Houſes, or ſo much as a bare order of either, neceſſity will notwithſtanding ſufficiently warrant &amp; inſtruct the people, as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and lawfully, though not ſo readily, to defend themſelves from ruine and deſtruction; grant then that the danger be imminent, the neceſſity is implied therein, and all the reſt will follow: This is a truth, though ſuch a one as muſt be juſtly ballanced, and tenderly made uſe of; it is no doctrine of libertiniſme, though libertines ſhould abuſe it, and for a curbe to ſuch as would flie out on either ſide: If all fortifications throughout the Kingdome were once demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, it would be to little purpoſe for a King to require more of the Subjects then the Laws permit, and they had willingneſſe to performe: or for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives to engage the Kingdome farther then they that choſe them, ſhall unanimouſly approve thereof: And ſince the ſtrength and power is naturally in the people, as God doubtleſſe allowes thereof, that they might have a poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſhelter themſelves againſt the extremities of tyranny in what government ſoever; ſo will none truly conſcientious, eaſily take occaſion hereby to deny ſubjection to the Powers: It is not ſufficient to <hi>ſay</hi> there is imminent danger and neceſſity, both God and man muſt <hi>ſee</hi> it is ſo, and unleſſe we be both wiſe &amp; conſcientious in the mangage of it, ſtanders by and others, the Saints of all neighbouring States and Nations will judge otherwiſe thereof hereafter, what ever we our ſelves declare therein at preſent: what would the King or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament gaine thereby, if either of them did prevaile by ſword? in ſuch caſe the conquered party muſt be ſtill kept under by a martiall law and power, which would ſo long continue grievous to them both, untill the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be weary of it, and joyntly agree to caſt the yoke from off them; ſo that unleſſe the conditions be free, juſt and equall in apprehenſion of them both, Prerogative continued unto the King, Priviledges to both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Liberties unto the Subject, we cannot expect a during peace, much leſſe a Reformation of what is amiſſe either in Civill or Eccleſiaſticall affaires, nor Gods bleſſing upon any of them.</p>
            <p>Having thus heard what is alledged, and tryed and prepared our conſciences on both ſides let us thinke upon a Treaty, and rather then be without it, the wars
<pb facs="tcp:117052:3"/>
may ſtill be proſecuted, as if there were no Treaty? And becauſe it may ſeem that the King and Parliament doe not confide in one another, I wiſh with all meekneſſe and ſubmiſſion that they may both conſider whether it is not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that ſome ſuch middle way be thought on, as neither of them remaine at the meer power and mercy of the other, and yet it would not be good to divide the Kingdom again into a Heptarchie, or more, or fewer portions, but if it ſhould be thought fitting towards the compaſſing a ſpeedier disbanding of the Souldiers and demoliſhing all Inland works, whereby the Countrey is not only plundered of what they have at preſent, but abſolutely diſcouraged to till the ground, and nouriſh cattell, leſt both ſtocke and fruit be taken from them afterwards; that in this interim only, each of them may have a rationall ſecurity and ſafeguard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the others attempt, whileſt the bloud which hath been ſo long boyling, be growne cold againe, and every one of us better fitted and diſpoſed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace each other more cordially, that in ſuch caſe, and for ſuch purpoſe only, certaine garriſons for a ſhort time may ſtill remaine in ſome of the Sea-Ports as both King and Parliament ſhall approve of.</p>
            <p>For more facilitating of ſo good a worke, give me leave to premiſe theſe few things: 1. That the King being but one, cannot poſſibly overmatch the Subjects, unleſſe they will themſelves, and therefore the Houſes of Parliament may with leſſe danger treat him more like a King. 2. The King being ſole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of his owne, may better reſolve to forgoe the preſent enjoyment of ſome ſmall part there of a while, when He ſhall finde that God will trie Him, in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for it to purchaſe His owne peace, and three Kingdomes welfare, which both Houſes cannot comply in, unleſſe the major part be willing. 3. Though the generall good of all his Subjects ought rather to overſway a King, then all his owne intereſts in the Kingdome, yet ſince it is more barſh to Royall fleſh and bloud (borne to rule and governe others) to renounce their owne juſt rights, much more to deliver up unto the adverſe party, all ſuch as have adhered to Him; ſo may the Parliament expreſſe much Nobleneſſe and Wiſdome in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tender of preſſing Him with ſo great a tryall. 4. That though either ſide conceive the Propoſitions which ſhall be made unequall, and little hopes of bettering them for the preſent; yet I preſume the difference will not be ſo great, but both of them may expect ſecurity therein at time of need; and in caſe either ſide ſhould take advantage, and break out again, <hi>a good cauſe and conſcience with a leſſe Army, may more hopefully expect aſſiſtance from God to overcome a greater.</hi> 5. If Armes being laid downe on both ſides, the King through importunity of evill counſellours ſhould refuſe to paſſe any other Acts for redreſſe of ſundry grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances which the Subjects yet lye under, both Houſes have the ſame liberty to withold their conſent in ſuch other Acts as were for the Kings advantage, and I humbly propound whether it may not appeare upon enquiry, that (concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning civill intereſts) the Subjects, for the preſent, ſtand in leſſe need of new Acts to be paſſed in their favour then the King does of Subſidies, His Majeſty being no little indebted, His charge ſo much encreaſed, and His revenue leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. 6. If evill Counſellers or Courtiers ſhould returne againe to innovate
<pb facs="tcp:117052:4"/>
either in Church or State, they cannot have the boldneſſe or power to worke ſuch miſchieſe, but a trieniall Parliament will eaſily be able to make them wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it. And laſtly, That it cannot be for the good of King and People, that the three eſtates in Parliament, though Armes were quite laid downe, ſhould ſtand ſeverely upon the priviledge of their negative reſpective voyces, but neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily muſt comply with one another to make their mutuall happineſſe compleat.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I am verily perſwaded that one great reaſon which moved God to permit theſe Kingdomes to be thus divided, and engaged in a civill War, was the generall obſtinacie and averſeneſſe of moſt men of all ranks and qualities in each Nation, to tollerate, and beare with tender conſciences, and different opinions of their brethren, unleſſe they were thereunto ſo far neceſſitated, that without it, there muſt inevitably enſue on both ſides a totall ruine and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is full neare, the preſent wofull condition that all three, ſo lately flouriſhing Kingdomes, are now plunged into, God of his great mercy vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe effectually to ſhew them their deliverance: in this reſpect, as alſo in that I cannot thinke, that God hath ſuffered ſo much bloudſhed, either to eſtabliſh the Kings Prerogative, or the Priviledge of Parliament only, but that He hath yet a far greater worke of his own to bring about, I humbly conceive that Liberty of Conſcience may deſervedly require to be firſt treated on, what, and how far forth it may and ought to be permitted; which being throughly debated, and agreed on by both ſides as the firſt Article, to be forthwith ratified by the three citates in Parliament, all the reſt will doubtleſſe follow more willingly and ſweetly.</p>
            <p>If a man will raile againſt the high Commiſſion Court, or in a ſeditious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner revile Epiſcopacie or Presbytery, he ſhall not want multitudes to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and cry him up, but ſuch as in a Chriſtian way, goe about with meekneſſe to diſcover, and deſire the ſpring head may be reformed, the unwarrantable power of both witheld, from whence the ſpirituall wickedneſſes ariſe and without which, though we ſhould chance be eaſed a while by change, upon the aboliſhing of Prelacie, yet the milde and gentle <hi>interregnum,</hi> would prove ſo much more cruell to us afterwards, when a ſucceeding government, having the ſelfe ſame corrupting principles with Epiſcopacie, and knowing its own ſtrength, ſhall, <hi>contrary to Pauls doctrine, 2 Cor. 1. 24. aſſume againe the dominion of our conſciences,</hi> after we had taſted the ſweetneſſe of Chriſtian liberty, and flattered our ſelves with the continuance of it; ſuch I ſay, may run the hazard to be accounted preſumptuous, turbulent, or innovaters, ſo dim ſighted are moſt men in the <hi>myſtery of godlineſſe,</hi> and ſo inclinable to be tranſported with carnall wiſdome and ſecurity: It is not the imperiouſneſſe of <hi>Epiſcopacie, Preſbytery,</hi> or a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> in what degree of compariſon ſoever they ſhall ranke themſelves, which can ſecurge men into a ſpirituall Temple fit for the Holy Ghoſt to dwell in, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much conducing thereunto as a fatherly reproving, a brotherly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt patheticall beſeeching one another, like that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the bowels and tendereſt compaſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> practiſed by either of them in reſpect of what
<pb facs="tcp:117052:4"/>
they ought, and how little fruit we ſee thereof, I deſire no wayes to aggravate, but mention only, (God is my record) not ſo much for their ſorrow, as amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, having juſt cauſe to pray that I may finde repentance for my ſhare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which is not with the leaſt.</p>
            <p>Let both the <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>London</hi> party conſider duly, whether to be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted be not a ſigne of the true Church, ſince <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 12. <hi>All that will live godly muſt ſuffer perſecution,</hi> and conſequently though we had not one word more in all the Bible to this purpoſe, whether that government be not likelieſt to be ſuch as Chriſt intended to rule his people by, whom he calls his <hi>Sheep</hi> his <hi>Lambes, Joh.</hi> 21. 15, 16 no creatures of prey, which moſt reſpects, and bears with tender conſciences? and ſince all governments may degenerate into tyranny, though for the preſent, all things were ſettled according to either of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, whether notwithſtanding they ought not to wiſh, and even in meer po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie endeavour that there, might be a tolleration of weake conſciences, leſt through the viciſſitude and wheeling about of time, their owne conſciences might come againe to be oppreſſed hereafter: for <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaies, <hi>Ec.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>There is no new thing under the ſun, and the thing which hath been, is that which ſhall be done againe hereafter:</hi> and the generall applauſe and confidence which Epiſcopacie had ſo lately of its owne ſtrength in this Kingdome, ſhould be a warning for all other governments not to ſubject themſelves through preſumption of their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and party unto the like downfall and deſtruction: and ſuch as have either felt or underſtood the ſpirituall bondage which this Kingdome hath twice ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in time of Popery and Prelacie by reaſon of their coercive juriſdiction, unleſſe they be both earneſt with God and man, that the ſame be not given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any other government, will bring upon their owne ſoules, the miſcarriage of all ſuch as periſh through the tyranny which it will infallibly fall into the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe hereafter; it was not their Popery or Prelacie (that was to themſelves) which ſo much oppreſſed us, as their power, otherwiſe, the perſons of ſuch which ſtill remained in the ſame Popiſh and Prelaticall opinions, ought to have been rather proceeded againſt, and not that power to be arraigned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned both of ſpirituall and corporall rape and murder in Prelacie, which was ſo ſooner after to be again enthroned in Presbytery: I humbly querie what it might be that moved both Houſes of Parliament to vote and prepare a Bill againſt Epiſcopacie, or that prevailed with the Eſtates of <hi>Scotland</hi> to declare it Antichriſtian; if it were only an abuſing of ſuch power as was given to the Church, and might poſſibly have been well imployed, then may a Reformation or puniſhing of ſuch Biſhops as abuſed it, redreſſe our grievances, and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſtill remaine eſtabliſhed; but if it were the great <hi>Diana, Act.</hi> 19. 24, 28. that ſtrumpet and Idol which is common to them all, that plenepotentiary juriſdiction to adminiſter or paſſe ſentence againſt their brethren in perſon or eſtate, by vertue of a coercive diſcipline and dominion, how can it ſafely be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto any other government, ſince that <hi>both Popular and Ariſtocraticall with all others, are as infallibly, though not equally ſubject to tyrannize, as the Papaller E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall?</hi> And whereas it is ſaid that Presbytery diſclaimes coercive power to
<pb facs="tcp:117052:5"/>
be in the Church, but about it only to be imployed by the Civill Magiſtrate in behalfe and benefit of the Church, I would faine be informed, whether the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Magiſtrate be Judge when it is fitting to imploy ſuch power for behoofe of the Church; and if he be, whether then the Civill Magiſtrate be not above the Church, and every member and the whole Church lyable to correction though they offend not in their owne opinions; and if the Civill Magiſtrate may not move therein untill the Church or Presbytery require, whether ſuch may not be ſaid the Churches uſing of the Civill ſword in a more ſuperlative and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigne way, little differing from what they practiſe in the Papacie, which is firſt to degrade and diſrobe all Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and ſo deliver up, both them and all others that ſhall be found guilty unto the Civill Magiſtrate, which may not refuſe to ſee the execution done.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it may be objected that many places of Scripture herein alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, may as well ſeem to ſpeake for a tolleration of Popery, and my ſelfe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to plead for it, let ſuch be pleaſed to reſt ſatisfied, that though I cannot for the preſent make full diſcovery in the word of God, why, or how Papiſts ſhould be forced by fines and other penalties to be of <hi>our</hi> Religion, yet I take not upon me to be ſpokeſman for a tolleration of <hi>theirs,</hi> by reaſon of their Idolatry; but my humble deſires are proſtrated unto the King and Parliament that all other Chriſtians who are now reproached under the name of Puritans, Separatiſts or Nonconformiſts of what kind ſoever, who are ſo far from being ſuſpected, that they muſt needs be acknowledged the greateſt enemies to Idolatry, may enjoy ſuch peace and freedome, as will permit them to keep alwayes a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence both before God and man, <hi>Act.</hi> 24. 16. And that they would vouchſafe, out of the love they beare to Gods Cauſe and People, to take into further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that if as Reformed Proteſtants, we may not ſuffer Papiſts and Turks to make profeſſion of their Religion amongſt us, in a qualified and more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate manner, as in ſome parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> where they have Churches, but are not permitted their publicke Proceſſions, or open expoſing of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as they call it, which no Proteſtants can walke the ſtreets about, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being ſubject to be ſcandalized thereat, how far, in ſuch caſe, it may be found agreeable to the Word of God, for Proteſtants to tranſplant themſelves by Colonies, or as particular Marchants to goe and live in <hi>Turky,</hi> or in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> eſpecially, where, though they were not troubled with the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though they were not forced to Church, which they frequent notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to prevent the danger of it, though they might enjoy their owne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion quietly, whether they may for this reſpect live in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> where they cannot chuſe but ſee (and muſt likewiſe ſeem to countenance by putting off of hats, ſetting out lights, adorning with pictures, hangings, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that part of their houſes where the Proceſſion paſſes, ſometimes with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall kneeling, and ſeldome without bowing) even at their owne windows, and in the ſtreets as they walke about their buſineſſe, the ſuperſtitious pagean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of their wil-worſhip, and Idolatry, which is the condition of all our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Travellers that go amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:117052:5"/>
And whereas many will not ſticke to ſay, that ſuch are luke-warme or of no Religion, who deſire a tolleration of ſo many: I anſwer, That it is the freedome of their owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which they deſire, not to be indifferently of any Religion, or prophanely of none at all, but that they might enjoy alwayes peaceably that Religion, which they have examined and found to be the true one, and not be ſubject to a change ſo often as the Civill State, or thoſe of the higheſt Court ſhall pleaſe to vary; for ſince they are choſen anew ſo often as a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is called, they may every time be of different, if not of oppoſite opinions and religions; and far more is it to be feared, that ſuch will be found careleſſe, if not negligent, in the choice of their Religion, as little troubling themſelves to <hi>trie the ſpirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whether they be of God or no,</hi> 1 John 4. 1. or examine the opinions and doctrines which are taught, receive them currantly, what ever they be, ſo they come ſealed and delivered by authority of State.</p>
            <p>It hath more then once come into my thoughts, what might move the wiſdome of God, to leave the Scriptures ſo liable to the diverſities of interpretations, which in regard it ſavoured more of curioſity then ediſying, I purpoſely forbore to ruminate thereon; however at the ſame inſtant, it came into my minde as not altogether impoſſible, that God might be ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to make men more diligent and inquiſitive to ſearch after truth, and conſcientious in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing it <hi>with fear and trembling,</hi> Phil. 2. 12. after which manner we are required to <hi>work out our ſalvation:</hi> In this reſpect, the very Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> conſiſting in a dead letter, which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel himſelfe could ſcarce controvert or pick a quarrell with, did not render the Jews ſo ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and conſcionable, as the Goſpel doth Chriſtians; and even amongſt all thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſtianity, I conceive it may eaſily be obſerved, that ſuch as ſtudy the variety of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and trie the ſpirits out of a zeale to truth, chooſing their Religion by their owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, though erronious, are yet more jealous of Gods worſhip, and conſcionable towards men. Shall men ſo far diſtruſt themſelves to feare they may be miſled into a falſe religion or opinion, becauſe they have liberty to make profeſſion of the truth? or can a man be in a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condition then he can wiſh himſelfe to be? are we the more acceptable to God becauſe we will not be of the true Religion, unleſſe we be forced thereto? or are we the more excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable in being of the falſe, becauſe we are willing to be compelled into it? is the tyranny of the body ſo grievous to us, and are we in love with ſpirituall bondage? To be of a Religion becauſe it is countenanced by the law in that Countrey where thou liveſt, or becauſe moſt men are of the ſame, is no good reaſon; it is not a hundred yeares ſince Popery was eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by law in England, and may be ſo againe for all that we can tell, moſt part of Europe ſtill being Papiſts: Dear Reader, ſearch, examine thine owne heart, and conſider whether it may not be found in the laſt day, that many men have taken up that Religion which was with moſt importunity thruſt upon them, rather then they would take paines to make triall of it: Oh, but ſome will ſay it is preſumption to be wiſer then a Synod or a State; conſider againe, I beſeech thee in the feare of God, who is more arrogant and preſumptuous, he that ſeeketh to enjoy his owne conſcience peaceably, only admoniſhing and informing ſuch as run erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wayes with all humility and love, or thoſe that imperiouſly, and will they nill they, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine others to make profeſſion of ſuch opinions as they themſelves are of? and yet there is no <hi>medium</hi> between an implicite faith, and that which a mans owne judgement and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding leads him to.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſtill object and ſay, what ſhall be done to thoſe that are obſtinately malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and maliciouſly perverſe in their owne opinions? I anſwer, That as in the Parable it is ſaid, <hi>If they hear not Moſes and the Prophets, neither will they be perſwaded, though one roſe from the dead,</hi> Luke 16. 31. So if informing, exhorting, and ſuch fair means, or others which are Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture proofe, doe not prevaile with ſuch as are led into falſe opinions, harſh and compulſive, or other which are unwarrantable cannot, and therefore to charge a man that he is wilfully blinde, and will not ſee the truth, if he ſubmit himſelfe to heare and read what ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully required of him in that behalfe, is the moſt <hi>uncivill, unreaſonable,</hi> and <hi>unchriſtianlike</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that words know how to utter, and flatly againſt all reaſon, ordinary policie, &amp; Scripture, to endeavour or think that the myſticall Body of our Saviour may poſſibly be built up after
<pb facs="tcp:117052:6"/>
ſuch a manner, as it ſhould alwayes remaine in continuall fear and power of men to pull it downe againe; and though we ſhould ſuppoſe, that this very man who is thus reproached, had yeelded and complied in whatſoever could have been expected from him, yet it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to be in heart of this or that opinion, to beleeve this or that doctrine of truth, untill God had touched his heart, and called him thereunto, till when they ought ſtill in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to <hi>inſtruct even thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledgement of truth,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 25. as appears more largely in the following Diſcourſe: We ſay that Church Papiſts are moſt dangerous, and hypocrites the worſt of men, what ground have we then, or how can we excuſe our provoking them to goe to Church, or tempting them to be ſuch by ſo many ſeverall waies? that may be lawfull to one who thinks ſo, which to another would be ſin, becauſe he doubts thereof: have we not learned that eating of meats only was ſin in ſome good Chriſtians, 1 Cor. 8. 10, 11. when others might freely eat thereof without any guiltineſſe at all? how much more may the ſame caſe happen in points of diſcipline or doctrine, wherein the worſhip of God is more highly intereſſed and concerned.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe my ſelfe much inferiour to the taske I have undertook, and ſhould in no ſort have preſumed upon it, had I not apprehended my ſelfe to be called thereunto, through the ſilence of ſo many who were abundantly better qualified to undergoe it; however I doubt not but God will be ſo far forth pleaſed to ſecond my weak endeavours, as ſundry well diſpoſed ſouls may be provoked to light their torches at theſe ſparkles, and proſecute it with more advantage; for this cauſe am I moved to make them publick, not for any private reſpect or intereſt of mine own, further then they are involved in the generall; for if at any time I ſtood in need of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and freedome in mine own particular, I am not ſuch a ſtranger to forreigne Countries, both of ſeverall climates and profeſſions, but that I can finde the way thither againe to purchaſe my enlargement.</p>
            <p>I know I have not obſerved the ſymmetrie and rules of Architecture in contriving ſo large a Portall for ſo ſmall a Fabrick, however, before I take my leave, let me advertiſe thee, that I plead not againſt, but for liberty, and that the beſt of all liberties, the Liberty of Conſcience; not for, but againſt impriſoning, ſining, or tormenting, of all others the moſt tyrannicall, for matters meerly of Religion; not for, but againſt the ſhedding bloud, Chriſtian bloud, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant bloud of the moſt conſcientious Chriſtians, Gods deareſt Saints, the Lords inheritance, for whoſe ſalvation only our Saviour ſhed his owne moſt precious bloud. Dear Reader, let but the thought hereof prevail with thee to demurre a little, and conſider, whether this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, about liberty or bondage, life and death both temporall and ſpirituall, though hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeldome thought on, be not worth debating; <hi>Nulla unquam de morte hominis cunctatio long<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> diſclaime all cornall wiſdome which knew not what to counſell thee; renounce thine owne ſelf will and wiſhes, that fooliſhly have wiſhed and willed ſo many things unduly, as had not God witheld them from thee, muſt needs have been thy finall ruine: And now at laſt, fit and prepare thy minde to receive in ſuch further light and truth, as the Bleſſed Spirit ſhall pleaſe to viſit thee withall, and reſt aſſured, that God who now ſtands looking out for ſuch labourers, wil in ſome degree and meaſure according to thy readineſſe, make thee an inſtrument of a <hi>ſanctified peace and reformation,</hi> where with three Kingdomes are now in travell, to his owne glory, and thy eternall happineſſe: Which God of his infinite goodneſſe beſtow upon thee, and all ſuch as in ſincerity ſeek <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Truth:</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>BEſides miſpointing, the Errata are many, and ſome of them very groſſe, in which reſpect the Reader will doubtleſſe finde the benefit thereof, if before he proceed any further he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to rectifie theſe that follow, viz. Page 4. lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 17. for periſh, read perſiſt. ibid. p. l. 35. take. p. 6. l. 13. ingenuous. ib. p. l. 38. Barbery p. 9. l. 12. many times. p. 10. l. 20 perſiſt. p. 12. l. 22. whence. p. 14. l. 26. thoſe. p. 18. l. 33. ingenuous. p. 20. l. 5. doubting. p. 22. l. 14. make. p. 24. l. 39. one on. p. 28. l. 32 expreſſely. ib. p. l. 41. theſe. p. 29. l. 3. cannot poſſibly. p. 30. l. 29. with. p. 32. l. 13. make. p. 33. l. 11. apprehended. p. 47. l. 15. from though he write, to the end of l. 17. muſt come in at l. 20. after Beza. p. 49. l. 22. extraordinarily. ib. p. l. 29. us. ib. p l. 38. principles. p. 50. l. 12. your. ib. p. l. 27. as is yet. p. 51. l. 41. rather than. p. 55. l. 20. have not. p. 56. l. 6. principles.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117052:6"/>
            <head>Liberty of Conſcience: OR, <hi>The only means to obtain</hi> PEACE <hi>and</hi> TRUTH.</head>
            <p>THE Sword, Peſtilence, and Famine, are the three moſt dreadfull ſcourges wherewith God uſes to chaſtiſe a ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne People; and although that Sinne be the only gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſe to pull downe vengeance, and God ordinarily makes uſe of naturall meanes to convey it upon us in what kinde ſoever; yet in the former, man appeares to be a more principall and immediate inſtrument, then in the two latter, and doubtleſſe by Gods permiſſion, hath a greater liberty and power to beginne, and put an end to it, which was the cauſe that the Sword onely hath deſtroyed far more without compariſon, then Famine and peſtilence together: wherefore when <hi>David</hi> found himſelfe in a ſtrait by the three propoſitions of Sword, Peſtilence and Famine. which God made unto him as a puniſhment for <hi>numbring of the people,</hi> knowing full well the cruelties of man, choſe to fall into <note place="margin">1 Chron. 25.</note> the hand of God, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>therefore ſent the Peſtilence upon Iſraell, which in this reſpect beſides others may juſtly be thought the more mercifull of all three, and by conſequence of what was ſaid, it will follow, that ſuch as have the keeping of the Sword, with power to draw and put it up again, muſt be accountable for all the bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: Had Kings no other thornes about their Crownes, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe this one if duly thought on, would keep them circumſpect and watchfull in every action, the leaſt whereof, though inſenſibly, conduces ſomewhat towards Peace or Warfare.</p>
            <p>Warres, and rumours of warres have ever beene, and are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent throughout the world; but ſince Princes became Chriſtians, it may have been obſerved, how Chriſtendome a ſpot of ground only, hath continually been the Cock-pit, &amp; all the world beſides but as a breathing place; however we ought not for this cauſe to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in juſtifying Wars the more, but rather make ſearch and ſtrict enquiry whence it comes to paſſe, that Chriſtians are ſo plunged therein, ſince they of all other people can juſtifie it leaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117052:7"/>
I know there may be a juſt-War, but what I am now to ſay, is meant only againſt that which is unjuſt, and ſo deſire it may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, whereof I doe the more preſume becauſe no Warre but hath much evill as the effect thereof; and however for ſuch as do begin a War, we may charitably conceive of both ſides, that they apprehend it to be lawfull, yet if we examine ſtanders by, and heare what all that are not intereſſed doe judge thereof, we ſhall finde them generally condemning both ſides, though one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in a greater meaſure than another.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, that <hi>covetouſneſſe is the root of all evill,</hi> and Warre <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 10.</note> which is the greateſt of thoſe evills, queſtionleſſe was never yet without a coveting; however, becauſe that neither coveting, nor ſuch other motives as are the reall and originall cauſes of taking up of Armes, have not for the moſt part beene found, or thought ſufficient to prevaile, or beare ſway enough with all ſuch as are to be required to contribute largely for the maintenance thereof; I ſay, it may moſt commonly be obſerved, that whatſoever were the reall, though more ſecret ground of War, Religion was ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be the principall, or at leaſt endeavoured to be made ſeem ſo far forth hazarded and engaged in the quarrell, that no man might adventure to call in queſtion the lawfulneſſe thereof, or ſeem backward in ſupplying without palpable ſcandall and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of luke-warmneſſe in Religion: I need not bring examples for proofe hereof, every mans own acquaintance in Hiſtories will furniſh himſelfe abundantly.</p>
            <p>But in regard that Religion, though perhaps it ſeldome was the primary and ſole cauſe of making War (in that I thinke few have been ſo conſcientious, yet ſuch as ſome Caſuiſts conceive, were but a miſgrounded conſcience in reſpect of an offenſive War) hath notwithſtanding been, and ſtill is the moſt powerfull meanes and ſtratagem to countenance and continue it, whereby that which ought to be moſt deare and ſacred, becomes a pander to ſatisfie our luſts, the conſideration whereof, the ſhedding ſo much Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian bloud, the obſtructing of the Goſpels propagation, the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable devaſtation of whole Countries, with infinite perpetrating and multiplication of moſt enormous and execrable villanies, have moved me to conſider with my ſelfe, which way Religion might be vindicated and redeemed from this abuſe, the grand meanes of fomenting. Wars diſcovered, the main jealouſies prevented which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117052:7"/>
Princes pretend to have of one another, or King and people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, towards accommodation of the preſent Wars, and cutting off occaſion from ſuch as otherwiſe might ſpring up againe hereafter.</p>
            <p>Whether Religion have been the reall cauſe of ſo much War in Chriſtendome, or ſo pretended only, makes all one to what I have in hand, which is to prove in this Diſcourſe, by Gods aſſiſtance, how a man ought not to be perſecuted for conſcience ſake, as will appeare by the inconſiſtencie thereof with ſundry Scriptures fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which being once concluded on, and put in practice, will make an open way for the free paſſage of the Goſpel, quite cut off the greateſt jealouſies and feares which perplex the mindes of Princes, States and People, when they ſuppoſe or but alleadge an endangering of their Religion, and conſequently the likelieſt courſe of reducing all Chriſtian Countries to peace amongſt themſelves, and friendly intercourſe with * one another.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>You are bought with a price, be ye not the ſervants of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 7. 22, 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>men:</hi> this muſt be meant for matters of this world, or elſe of that which is to come; about ſubjection of the body in civill affaires, or ſubjection of the ſoule in ſpirituall; but it cannot be underſtood for matters of the body, or of this world, becauſe it would then contradict other places of Scripture, which command <hi>all to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1. 1 Pet. 2 13. Eph. 5 22. and 65. 1 Pet. 2. 8. Col. 3. 22.</note> 
               <hi>unto higher Powers, ſervants to their maſters, wives to their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,</hi> and the like; in which reſpect, as alſo from the coherence with the words aforegoing, it appeares neceſſarily to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that we muſt not be ſubject concerning our Religion, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of conſcience or touching the ſoule, to be of this or that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, becauſe we are commanded by King or State, for though it be the true Religion which we profeſſe, yet if we were forced to it, it will doe us little good, nor be ever a whit available, for God accepts only of willing ſervice, ſuch as we performe of our owne free election, not by compulſion.</p>
            <p>Neither is the objection good, that though men be forced into <note place="margin">Object.</note> the true Religion at firſt without any liking of their owne, yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards it falls out that ſuch approve of it, and will not bee brought to change nor alter, which muſt needs be acceptable to God: For firſt, the compelling of a man to any thing againſt his <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> owne conſcience, eſpecially in matters of faith, is a <hi>doing evill,</hi> which God forbids, <hi>that good may come of it,</hi> and therefore we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 8. and 14. 23.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117052:8"/>
expect that he ſhould proſper, ſo bad a meanes to produce ſo good effect, as that people at firſt conſtrained to make profeſſion of the true Religion, ſhould afterwards prove ſincere and true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, by vertue of thoſe coercive powers which were meerly unwarrantable and ſinfull, but for ſuch as doe ſo continue, it is to be attributed to ſome other meanes whereby they became con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the truth, or more ſecret call of God, which would in due time have found out, and brought them home into his ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold without the helpe of a tyranous inquiſition.</p>
            <p>This is more evident if we conſider the multitudes of people and whole Nations which live and dye in the Religion they were borne, with equall conſtancie and ſecurity, though their faith and tenets be diametrically oppoſite to one another; and for thoſe that happen to be thus of the true Religion, becauſe borne in it, though it be the true one, and that they will not be brought to change, yet for moſt part they can give no better reaſon of their faith, then thoſe that are in the wrong, and periſh as obſtinately, for they tooke not their Religion upon choice or triall, neither do they continue it upon judgement, never having ſearched or tried the Scriptures, as we are commanded; and indeed they may well ſay, to what purpoſe ſhall we <hi>examine our ſelves,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>whether we be in the faith or no?</hi> to what end, <hi>Try the ſpirits whether</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5. 1 Joh. 4. 1. Gal. 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>they be of God?</hi> or, <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> whether the doctrine taught us now be the ſame which the Apoſtles left us? when we may not profeſſe the Religion we apprehend to be the only true one, but are forced to make profeſſion of that only which the State ſhall thinke fit, and declare to be ſuch.</p>
            <p>Nay, in that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>Trie the ſpirits whether they bee of God or no;</hi> and tells them plainly, that <hi>if any man thinke himſelfe to be ſomething, then he is nothing, that he deceiveth himſelfe, and that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhould therefore prove his owne worke, and that then he ſhall have rejoycing in himſelfe alone, and not in another, for every man ſhall beare his owne burthen, Gal.</hi> 6. 3, 4, 5. And to the Theſſalonians he ſaies, <hi>Prove all things, and hold faſt that which is good, 1 Theſſ.</hi> 5. 21. Do not ſuch thwart and reſiſt theſe Scriptures, who take upon them to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne and ſtint men unto certaine ſpirits, as though they could be ſaved by the faith and knowledge of others, with expreſſe peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory commands to receive them for the true Spirit of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any triall or examination? and indeed it is better to take up a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117052:8"/>
Religion without triall upon adventure, then having examined and found it Antichriſtian or erronious, ſubmit unto it notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; but certainly if well examined, this will appeare not a bare <hi>adding or taking from the word of God,</hi> but a flat oppoſition, and giving the lie, as I may terme it, unto the Scriptures, for whom a heavier judgement is preparing, if ſuch a one were poſſible, then that which is denounced in the Revelation. <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 18, 19</note>
            </p>
            <p>What if the Prince and Peeres ſhould change Religion, muſt they be ſubject alſo to perſecution? I know not how they can be well ſecured ſo long as ſuch Statutes are in force; for in that they concerne matters of Religion, if they binde at all, they binde moſt of all: But what if a King and Parliament ſhould repeale all Acts againſt the Papiſts, and paſſe others of the ſame tenour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Proteſtants, muſt we therefore all turne Papiſts? If that Religion muſt be received and forced upon the conſciences of people, which by a major part is voted to be the true one, I know no remedy but that we may be lyable againe hereafter to change as often as thoſe that lived in the Reignes of <hi>Henry 8. Edward</hi> 6. Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My humble deſires therefore are, that we may not procraſtinate any longer the preventing ſo great a miſery, as the world cannot poſſibly torment us with a greater, not through confidence of a preſent prevailing party, or ſuch other aſſurance as carnall policie and wiſdome doe only furniſh us withall; the Biſhops condition may be ſufficient item to us in this behalfe, who, notwithſtanding ſo many ſuffered by them, had within leſſe then five yeares ſince greater multitudes of abettors within this Kingdome, then ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kinde of Church government in likelihood will find hereafter; it is neceſſary therefore to proceed upon a ſure foundation, by paſſing an act againſt perſecution for Religion, which beſides the agreeableneſſe with Scripture, all degrees of people having once taſted the ſweetneſſe of it, will never ſuffer themſelves to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved thereof againe, and by that means become a ſure eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of the generall peace of the Kingdome, and diſpoſe every one more willingly to ſubmit to higher powers, though to ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of his propriety when he apprehends himſelf certain to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Liberty of his Conſcience.</p>
            <p>But may we <hi>not any longer be ſubject unto men?</hi> Surely then in <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 22, 23</note> whatſoever ſenſe it be meant, we muſt be ſubject unto Chriſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117052:9"/>
               <hi>his yoke is eaſie;</hi> and we muſt not live lawleſſe as we our ſelves liſt, <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 30.</note> but perſecution impoſes a heavier yoke of ſubjection upon the Conſcience, then any Prince or Tyrant in the world doth upon the body of his Subjects: And although every ſoule muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to higher Powers in civill matters, yet there are degrees of ſubjection and relations in a Common-wealth whereby one is bound to yeeld more or leſſe ſubjection, obedience, reſpect, and honour, according to the reſpective Lawes and ranke wherein he ſtands; and yet in moſt Countries every Subject from the higheſt to the loweſt hath a kinde of freedome, and poſſibility of quitting himſelfe from the moſt toilſome and inferiour vaſſalage, if he be a man of abilities or wealth; but that Law which impoſes on the Conſcience, ſerves all alike, ſave that the moſt ingenious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious <note place="margin">Note.</note> are moſt afflicted with it, and ſo long as it is in force, a good Conſcience hath no meanes either to evade it or diſpence with it.</p>
            <p>But how fruitleſſe a courſe it is to force men to conformity in a Religion they have no liking of, will appeare by the ſmall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe it wrought on Papiſts here in <hi>England,</hi> many whereof went to Church when they were ſtrictly lookt too, ſtopping their eares with wooll becauſe they would not heare at all, or heare with an intention to beleeve the contrary; or elſe like Proteſtant Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and travellers in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> which ordinarily goe to Maſſe and Veſpers, to avoid ſuſpition of the Inquiſition, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their hearts joyn not in the Church devotions, they purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſend their eyes a gadding after beauty, whileſt many, too too many, by cuſtome aſſume ſo great a liberty, as if the eye could not ſin in one reſpect, whileſt the heart conſented not in another, or rather as if God would pardon them the luſt of the eye, ſo long as they were not Popiſh in their hearts.</p>
            <p>But more remarkable it is in the Moores of <hi>Spaine</hi> and Jewes of <hi>Portugal,</hi> ſome whereof diſſembled Popery in their ſucceſſive ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations ſome hundreds of yeares together, untill the Moores be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcovered in ſuch multitudes, as that the King not thinking it ſafe to retaine them longer in ſo ſlaviſh a captivity of the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor able to give them a tolleration without the Popes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pencing, commanded them to be gone, and accordingly about the yeare 1606. they conveyed themſelves into <hi>Barbaria</hi> and <hi>Turkey,</hi> with ſuch a ſtocke of Chriſtian crafts and pollicie, as not only the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117052:9"/>
Pirates, but thoſe whole Nations are much advantaged and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, to the no leſſe ſhame than detriment of Chriſtianity: Oh let not the like befall <hi>England,</hi> with her manufactors, but I feare it is almoſt too late to wiſh ſo, for ſo many thouſands of them being already gone, are able to teach all the world, unleſſe both they be ſuddenly recalled, and others encouraged to continue by a Liberty of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>And for the Jewes in <hi>Portugall,</hi> the Inquiſition uſed alwaies to be full of them, ſeldome without foure hundred or five hundred together, and though moſt of them will not ſcruple, and many of them chuſe rather to marry with ſuch as really are Chriſtians, that they may with more ſecurity play the hypocrites, yet by ſuch as live amongſt them it is obſerved, that though from one generation to another, they have matched into Chriſtian families, yet they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and inſtill their Jewiſh principles ſo ſubtilly into their off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, as the children though they have remaining in them not above one two and thirtieth part of a Jew, are notwithſtanding knowne by infallible preſumptions to be Jewes in heart, though outwardly they make profeſſion otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>In the Goſpel according to St. <hi>John, Jeſus</hi> anſwered, <hi>My</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 18. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Kingdome is not of this world, if my Kingdome were of this world, then would my ſervants fight that I ſhould not be delivered up to the Jewes.</hi> What can be more oppoſite unto the intentions and proceedings of our Saviour, who rather than reſiſt choſe to ſuffer perſecution unto death, than theſe that perſecute others unto death? If Chriſts Kingdome be not of this world, but if it be myſticall and ſpirituall, then muſt it neceſſarily be erected by powerfull preaching of the Word; and by the Spirit: When <hi>Peter.</hi> ſmote off the high Prieſt ſervants care in defence of his Maſter, our Saviour bids him put <hi>up</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 51, 52.</note> 
               <hi>his ſword,</hi> and inſtead of commending him and his zeal in reſcuing the ſacred Perſon of our bleſſed Saviour, ſaies, <hi>All they that take the ſword ſhall periſh by the ſword:</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts the Epheſians <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 10. 17.</note> to <hi>be ſtrong,</hi> but <hi>in the Lord, and in the power of his might,</hi> not bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhing the ſword of civill Magiſtrates, but <hi>to take the belmet of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God:</hi> and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place he ſayes, that <hi>Faith comes by hearing, and how ſhall they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in him they have not heard? and how ſhall they heare without a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 14. 17</note> 
               <hi>preacher?</hi> And yet if it had been as good a way, <hi>Paul</hi> would doubtleſſe have taught it them, by ſaying, how ſhall they beleeve
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117052:10"/>
unleſſe you tell them? and how ſhall they know what is to bee beleeved, unleſſe you impoſe it upon them? But this was none of <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine; both our Saviour and his Apoſtles not only taught and practiſed, but ſealed the contrary with their bloud.</p>
            <p>The Spaniards are blamed, and that juſtly, by all other Nations for having maſſacred ſo many millions of Weſt-Indians in their owne Country, under pretence of Religion, though it be evident, it was only that they might the eaſier rifle them of their gold and ſilver, and ſo it is in all perſecutions pretended for Conſcience ſake; for did we but a little conſider with our ſelves, we would eaſily conclude, that few have been yet ſo mad to put people to death meerly for Religion ſake; I know that many in paſſion, rage and fury, will ſay it is pity ſuch Hereticks ſhould live, but when ſuch men are in a calme mood, if another <hi>Nathan,</hi> like him that came to <hi>David,</hi> ſhould ſay unto them, there is ſuch a neighbour of mine <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 1.</note> charitable to the poore, upright in his dealing, courteous in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, meek and lowly minded, loyall to his Sovereigne, true to his Country, chuſing rather to ſuffer than offer injuries, beloved of all that knew him, and never ſo much as tainted with ſuſpition of any thing blame-worthy, till of late being accuſed as a Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt for ſeducing the Kings liege people unto his owne Religion; the Jury finding him guilty, he is condemned to dye; will not a tender hearted Chriſtian be ready to reply, it is pity ſuch a one ſhould dye? and though the Law condemne him, the King is mercifull, and doubtleſſe would reprieve him if he knew he had been loyall to his Country, and committed no other ſinne then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring by argument from Scripture to bring others of his owne Religion: now though moſt men, or every good man would be loth that a conſcientious Chriſtian ſhould be put to death for doing nothing but what he is bound in conſcience, the winning Proſelites to his cauſe, his religion, which amongſt ſo many different ſorts of Chriſtins, he thinks to be the right, and himſelfe no leſſe obliged to publiſh it, then <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> who when they were commanded by the Magiſtrate not to ſpeake or <note place="margin">Acts 4. 17. 10.</note> teach in the name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> anſwered, <hi>We cannot but ſpeake the things which we have ſeen and heard:</hi> And when our Saviour ſent out his Apoſtles, he ſaid unto them, <hi>What I tell you in darkneſſe, ſpeake ye in light, and what ye hear in the ear, that preach ye upon the houſe tops, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 17, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>feare not them which kill the body,</hi> cut are <hi>not able to kill the ſoule:</hi> Now
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117052:10"/>
though Chriſtians generally will not acknowledge that they put any to death meerly for Conſcience ſake, yet ſo long as there is a Law where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſuch as differ from us in religion, or any point thereof ſhal be more lyable then our ſelves: as the Jewes, <hi>when they could not reſiſt and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay the ſpirit wherewith Steven ſpake, ſtirred up the people, ſuborned and ſet up falſe witneſſes to accuſe him, Acts</hi> 6. 11. 13. So, amongſt us there will not be wanting one or other who for ſome private intereſt and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect, will finde out one to accuſe, others to witneſſe, a Jury to give verdict and make guilty, a Judge to pronounce the ſentence, and at laſt finde meanes to keep the King from reprieving, all of them thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring to put him to death by the advantage of ſuch a Law, whereas really it was not his Religion which they ſo much regarded, and they may cleerly ſay they put him not to death for his Religion, but it was their owne reſpective private benefit and ends which corrupted them to compaſſe his diſtruction by force and colour of ſuch a Law.</p>
            <p>But why? what reaſon which is Scripture proofe can be given, why a particular Gentleman ſhould be put out of a Mannor whereof he hath the propriety by inheritance or purchaſe, more than a whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Nation of Infidells and Pagans for Religion ſake? Perhaps it <note place="margin">Object.</note> may be ſaid, the State hath enacted a Law whereby this Gentlemans whole revenue or part of it becomes forfeited, becauſe he is not of the true Religion; whereto I anſwer, That Popery was enacted to be the true Religion in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, and that which Proteſtants pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> yet they could not be both the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, however the Subject was not ſuffered to ſay ſo much of either, ſo long as they had a Parliament protection; but doubtleſſe all juſt Laws have their grounds and rule in Scripture, and more exactly ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Religion, which is the <hi>unum neceſſarium:</hi> and if a Pagan Nation may not be invaded in their teritories, becauſe they will not be of our Religion, nor a neighbouring Chriſtian people differing from us in ſome opinions, why ſhould a particular man have <hi>his only lambe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 4.</note> his pittance taken from him for refuſing only to be of a religion, or of an opinion which would abſolute <hi>damne him becauſe he doubts,</hi> ſo long <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 23.</note> as he lives peaceably, and gives unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things which are <hi>Caeſars?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Geneſis we finde that <hi>Hamor</hi> and <hi>Sechem</hi> told the men of their City that <hi>Jacob and his children were peaceable, and therefore moved that they might dwell in the land and trade therein;</hi> but when <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> had treacherouſly ſlaine <hi>Hamor, Sechem,</hi> and all their males, whilſt they were ſore after their late circumciſion, though it was in revenge that <hi>Sechem</hi> had firſt defiled their ſiſter <hi>Dinah,</hi> yet <hi>Jacob</hi> reproved them
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117052:11"/>
ſaying ye have troubled me, and made me to ſtinke amongſt the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34. 2. 21. 25. 30. So when the Proteſtant Princes made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion to the Emperours of <hi>Germany,</hi> or Kings of <hi>France</hi> in behalfe of ſuch as profeſſed the reformed Religion: nay, when any Chriſtian Prince made meanes to Turke or Perſian that their ſubjects might live within their juriſdictions enjoying Liberty of Conſcience, doe we thinke they uſed any other arguments then that ſuch Chriſtians were peaceable harmleſſe men, medled not with the State or Government, and deſired only that they might be permitted to recide there, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the freedome of their Conſcience, where they had their revenues, friends, or beſt meanes to get a livelihood? they moved not that ſuch poore Chriſtians might not be perſecuted becauſe they were of the true Religion, for every man thinkes his owne to be the trueſt, and though he take advice of never ſo many, will not let another be finall judge thereof; for Turkes have as much reaſon to perſecute Chriſtians, as Chriſtians have to perſecute Turkes; but for Chriſtians to perſecute one another, and yet blame one another for the ſame perſecution; how can they chuſe but thinke St. <hi>Pauls</hi> reprehenſion was not ſo ſutable to the Romans, as themſelves? and how can they expect to avoid Gods judgements mentioned in the Text, ſo long as they periſh ſo wilfully, condemning others for what they doe themſelves? the words are theſe; Therefore <hi>thou art inexcuſable, O man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt, for wherein thou judgeſt another thou condemneſt thy ſelfe, for thou that judgeſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>doeſt the ſame things: And thinkeſt thou this, O man, that judgeſt them which doe ſuch things, and doeſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgement?</hi> Might not St. <hi>Paul</hi> if he were now living ſay, Thou Proteſtant, ſayeſt thou a man [a Calviniſt] ſhould not perſecute, and doeſt thou the ſame? Thou Calviniſt, ſayeſt thou a man [a Proteſtant] ſhould not perſecute, and doeſt thou the ſame? Since it is moſt true, that they muſt mutually juſtifie, or mutually condemne each other, and though it will be by both ſides alleadged, that none are put to death amongſt <note place="margin">Note.</note> them meerly for Religion ſake, I feare me, it may be found upon due ſcrutiny, how many have dyed on both ſides, as well for exerciſing their owne Religion, as ſeeking to convert others; and in regard that both Calviniſts, Lutherans, and all others of the reformed Religion have received and acknowledged our Saviours command to <hi>love their neighbours as themſelves,</hi> and <hi>doe to others as they would be done to,</hi> and <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 19. Luke 6. 31. and 22 32.</note> thinke they are no leſſe bound then St. <hi>Peter, when he was converted, to convert his brethren,</hi> and this being a doctrine and point of Faith, which all reformed Chriſtians make profeſſion of, ſuch of them as have been impriſoned, fined, baniſhed, or put to death, for no other cauſe but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117052:11"/>
what this point of their faith obliged them to, cannot be ſaid other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then to have beene thus perſecuted meerly for Religion ſake: And there is this more of aggravation, that for the moſt part theſe fierce and perſecuting Chriſtians eſteem each other in a damnable condition ſo long as they periſh and dye therein, and yet either of them being by the other condemned to death ſhall have his pardon, if he become a convert, which is a deſtroying of the ſpirit that the fleſh may be ſaved, juſt oppoſite to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine, but if he refuſe, they proceed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, which according to their owne opinion ſends them irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably to hell, whereas in Chriſtian charity they ought rather to reprieve them, that there might be a poſſibility of their converſion: and were we not beſotted with moſt ſupine careleſſenes or ignorance, wee ſhould not chuſe but ſee that perſecuting and putting to death the body of ſuch as differ from us in religion or opinion, cannot poſſibly be out of charity to their ſoules, but muſt needs acknowledge that either we are guilty of their periſhing both body and ſoule, if they dye in ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, or elſe condemne our ſelves on the other ſide for putting them to death, becauſe they were of ſuch a religion or opinion as accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pained them to heaven: If St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Corinthians preſcribes all <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 5</note> Chriſtians a way of proceeding againſt ſinners <hi>for deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of our Lord Jeſus;</hi> and if hee tels <hi>Timothy</hi> that <hi>a ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle unto all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 24, 25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>men, apt to teach, patient, in meekneſſe inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledgement of the truth, and that they may recover themſelves out of the ſnares of the Divell:</hi> what art thou, O Chriſtian, who contradicting the Holy Ghoſt in theſe places of Scripture, thus putteſt Chriſtians to death after ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and in ſuch a time, as that according to the faith whereof thou thy ſelfe makeſt profeſſion, the ſpirit of ſuch Chriſtians cannot poſſibly be ſaved, but muſt inevitably be damned in the day of our Lord Jeſus? conſider of it, I beſeech thee in the feare of God, and be humbled, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to redeem thine owne miſdoing by the grace of God, in earneſtly petitioning his divine Goodneſſe to diſpoſe the King and Parliament for repealing ſome lawes, and enacting others, whereby the people may be free hereafter from ſo dangerous a temptation, as this power and colour of perſecuting others for Religion ſake leads them unto.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not yet leave St. <hi>Paul</hi> without making a little more uſe of ſo bright a light, who reproving the Corinthians in that they ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch as committed fornication to live amongſt them, though abſent by virtue of his Apoſtleſhip, judged ſuch offenders to be taken from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117052:12"/>
them, and by the ſame authority commanded the Church of Corinth to <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 3, 4, 5.</note> put it in execution, &amp; that <hi>when they came together in the name of the Lord Jeſus, they ſhould deliver ſuch a one unto Sathan for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit might be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus:</hi> Now either this delivering up to Sathan was a preſent putting to death with a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous inference, that the ſudden putting to death is a ſaving of the ſoul, or elſe it is only ſome Eccleſiaſticall and Chriſtian cenſure whereby the ſinner might have liberty to ſurvive for the mortifying of his body and deſtroying all fleſhly luſts that the ſoule might eſcape in the dreadfull day of judgement, ſo that ſuch as put the body to death, as much as in them lyes, damn the ſoul, quite oppoſite to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> intention, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed another way of juſtice with his expreſſe reaſon for it, <hi>That the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>ſoule might be ſaved;</hi> wherefore they may well be reproved and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in his owne words to the Romans, <hi>Deſpiſeſt thou the riches of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>goodneſſe and forbearance and long ſuffering, not knowing that the goodneſſe of God leadeth thee to repentance?</hi> And whereas in other places, he ſaies, <hi>We are by Chriſt made able miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the letter, but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 6</note> 
               <hi>of the Spirit, for the letter killeth, but the Spirit giveth life;</hi> unleſſe in this, and ſuch other Scriptures, it be underſtood that the Goſpel diſpences ordinarily with the letter of the Law, to mitigate and qualifie temporall puniſhments of the body, as well as to free us from eternall torments of the ſoule; I doe not finde where Chriſtian people and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths <note place="margin">Exod. 21. 12. 15. 17. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v. 20. 10 and 24. 17 21. Num. 35. 16. &amp; ſeq. <hi>Object.</hi>
               </note> take power of ſparing ſuch offenders which by the expreſſe letter of the Law were commanded to be put to death.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, if men be ſuffered to preach ſuch groſſe erronious doctrines, the number of Hereticks would quickly be ſo great, that true Beleevers might be ſwallowed up by them, as good corne which is choaked many times through abundance of tares and weeds; whereto I anſwer, That we ſhould do that only which is commanded and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, relying upon Gods providence concerning the event, he <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> ſpares not theſe erronious Beleevers or Hereticks that they might ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and pervert the faithfull, for that is impoſſible, but that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full might in his due time reduce the misbeleevers unto the truth, who <note place="margin">Joh. 24. 24</note> if they ſhould be taken off preſently, would for all we can expect have periſhed in their ſinnes: And as St. <hi>Paul</hi> taught the Corinthians, <hi>If a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 12. 14. 16.</note> 
               <hi>brother have a wife that beleeveth not, and ſhe be pleaſed to dwell with him, let him not put her away, for the unbeleeving wife is ſanctified by the beleeving huſband, and what knoweſt thou O huſband, whether thou ſhalt ſave thy wife?</hi> Surely this text may be well applied to the whole Church which is the Spouſe of Chriſt, and ſuch as finally cut off the leaſt inferiour member by perſecution, be ſo much more juſtly cenſured and condemned by it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117052:12"/>
Our Saviour having ſent his meſſengers to a village of the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes <note place="margin">Luke 9. 32. &amp; ſeq.</note> to make ready for him, the people of the village refuſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, which when <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaw, <hi>they deſired to bring downe fire from heaven to conſume them as Eliah did,</hi> but <hi>our Saviour rebuked them,</hi> ſaying, <hi>ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of, for the Sonne of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them;</hi> I wiſh this Scripture were well conſidered on by all that make profeſſion of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The Inquiſitors of theſe dayes have no better ground for their ſtrict proceedings, then the Old Teſtament which expreſſely commanded <note place="margin">Exod. 34. 13. Deut. 7. 5. &amp; 12. 3. 2 King 18 4. Mich. 5. 14 2 King. 1. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Idolatry to be rooted out,</hi> their <hi>Altars to be pulled downe, and groves wherein they worſhipped falſe gods, to be deſtroyed;</hi> there have we alſo the example of <hi>Eliah, who conſumed the two Captaines with their fifties,</hi> which were ſent from the Idolatrous King <hi>Ahaziah:</hi> the Diſciples <hi>John</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> it ſeems, were then of the ſame mind in this reſpect, &amp; if they could have had their owne wills, would have cauſed fire from heaven to have rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon the oppoſers of the New Teſtament as <hi>Eliah</hi> had done upon the Idolatrous and diſobedient of the Old, but <hi>our Saviour who was very</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 29.</note> 
               <hi>meekneſſe,</hi> reproved them for not knowing what manner of ſpirit they were of, as if he ſhould have ſaid, you muſt not have the ſpirit of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuters; but ſuch a ſpirit as thoſe which are to be perſecuted have need of; and for this cauſe he had before taught them a leſſon of preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">Matth 10. 23, 24, 25.</note> ſaying, <hi>When they perſecute you in this City, flye ye into another, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple is not above his Maſter, nor the ſervant above his Lord: If they have called the Maſter of the houſe Beelzebub, how much more ſhall they call them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 12.</note> 
               <hi>of his houſhold?</hi> And for the deſtruction of the groves which had beene made to commit Idolatry in, if it concerne Proteſtant Reformers to do the like under the Goſpel, we ſhould not finde many Churches in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> which could eſcape; but whether they be all to be pulled down, or why one more then another, I leave it to ſuch as have already deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their opinions to make them good, wiſhing them to remember: that in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> judgement, a good Chriſtian <hi>might have eaten of thoſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. &amp; 10. cap.</note> 
               <hi>meats which had been conſecrated to their Idolls, provided it were no ſcandall to a weak beleever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although this leſſon was ſo quite contrary to the diſpoſitions of <hi>John</hi> and <hi>James</hi> ambitious when they reaſoned amongſt themſelves <hi>who</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 9. 46.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould be the greateſt,</hi> that they might in liklihood be the more enabled to perſecute and puniſh others, as appeared afterwards by this raſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſed motion of theirs, yet the reprehenſion in both reſpects ſunck ſo deep into their eares, that the Diſciples never exerciſed greatneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, nor perſecution or compulſion towards others, much leſſe preſcribed it to be practiſed by their ſucceſſors, and in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117052:13"/>
purſuance thereof, St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſed, or rather required the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 3. 2.</note> and in them all Chriſtians, that they <hi>give no offence; neither to the Iewes nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God,</hi> and to the Coloſſians he ſaies, <hi>walke in wiſdome to them that are without:</hi> Now what can be <note place="margin">Col. 1. 4.</note> more againſt the rules of wiſdome, then endeavouring to bring into the true Church ſuch as are without by a rigorous way of perſecution? we ſee by daily experience that men are by nothing ſo much obliged and engaged, as by courteſie and affable proceedings, theſe both win and keep the heart faſt, whilſt violence and conſtraint can at beſt, but prevaile upon the body, the ſoule even in that inſtant ſo much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienated, as the body and outward man was forced to play the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite and yeeld obedience.</p>
            <p>What poſſibility is there of converting Papiſts, Jewes, Turkes, or Infidels to the Faith upon ſuch grounds as moſt Chriſtians hold at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent? It is generally and truly agreed on, that we ought not to invade their Countries to diſpoſſeſſe them of it, or their meanes, becauſe they refuſe to imbrace Chriſtianity, and I have ſcarce ſo much as heard of any Proteſtants, or others of the reformed Religion (may it be ſpoken for their humbling and amendment) that ever employed themſelves to compaſſe their converſion meerly for Conſcience ſake; few of them have means to come to us, and if they had, how can we thinke they would be willing if they knew they might not live amongſt us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being forced to a new Religion, before their reaſon and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings were convinced in the truth thereof? and for the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, as alſo in that the Chriſtians in their new Plantations ſeek more after the wealth of the Country, then propagating of the Goſpel, the neighbouring people of theſe parts hate the very name of Chriſtians, make ſuch oppoſition againſt them as they are able, and at laſt, when they have no other remedy, flye further off, not one of a thouſand deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their ſociety or acquaintance: can any thing be more contrary to walking in wiſdome towards a people, then to practice ſuch courſes as make themſelves odious and hatefull, that they cannot get to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into their company? St. <hi>Paul</hi> having writ unto the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that they ſhould not accompany with fornicators, leſt they might <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 10, 11.</note> miſtake him, he explanes it to them afterwards, that it was not his meaning that they ſhould altogether forbeare to keep company with the fornicators of this world, or with the covetous or extortioners, or with Idolaters, for then they muſt needs go out of the world, but if a brother were ſuch a one, they ſhould <hi>not ſo much as eat with him;</hi> from hence I conceive may be inferred, that if the Diſciples of Chriſt had had a civill power to force a way for the Goſpel, yet they thought it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117052:13"/>
either not lawfull or not expedient to imploy ſuch meanes, becauſe they forbore to make uſe of milder, for though they might not eat with a profeſſor, a brother which was a notorious wilfull ſinner, yet ſuch as were without, though they were covetous, fornicators, extortioners, and Idolaters to boot, they might eat and keep company with them by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> permiſſion, when they might as well have avoided it in them <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 27.</note> as in their owne brethren; and whereas Idolatry and other execrable ſinnes were then ſo rife with all men, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was forced to ſay in effect, that it was not poſſible to live, and not keep company with ſuch ſinners, yet he ſaid not that ſuch as would altogether avoid their company, muſt ſend ſuch ſinners out of the world, or out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <note place="margin">Note.</note> by perſecution, which the Inquiſitors of theſe times practiſe, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuates, that in caſe the world were ſo full of notorious ſinners and misbeleevers, as that a true Beleever could not live in the world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out converſing with them, and that God would not permit his people to converſe with them, that then the true Beleevers themſelves ſhould rather goe out of the world, then ſend ſuch notorious ſinners and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleevers out of the world in the midſt of their ſinnes by perſecuting them to death, which I much deſire were well reflected on, as alſo that paſſage of St. <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpel in the prayer which our Saviour makes unto his Father in behalfe of his ſheep the true Beleevers, <hi>I pray not that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 17. 15</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhouldeſt take them out of the world, but that thou ſhouldeſt keepe them from the evill:</hi> from whence it may like wiſe be inferred, that if the true <note place="margin">Note.</note> Beleevers could not be kept from the ſinne and evill of the world, in ſuch caſe they ought rather to pray that God would be pleaſed to take themſelves out of the world, then to deſire that notorious ſinners or misbeleevers were taken out of the world in their ſins, whereas ſo long as they live there is hopes of their repentance.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour when he ſent forth his Diſciples, gave them charge to <note place="margin">Matth: 10. 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>preach the Goſpel freely as they had received it freely, and that if they came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch as would not receive or heare them, they ſhould depart thence ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off the duſt from their feet as a teſtimony againſt them,</hi> which is farre from a commiſſion to plant the Goſpel with fire and ſword, or other waies of perſecution, which are practiſed in theſe dayes; and Saint <hi>Marke</hi> in his relation thereof makes the commiſſion to be given them. <note place="margin">Marke 16. 15. 16.</note> in theſe words, <hi>Goe ye into all the world, and preach the Goſpel unto every creature, he that beleeveth and is baptized ſhall be ſaved, but he that beleeveth not ſhall be damned:</hi> Now though it be not to be meant ſo litterally and preciſely that they ſhould preach the Goſpel to irrationall creatures, yet the ſenſe and meaning of every creature is ſo cleare, that none which were capable to receive the word, ſhould be barred by perſecution from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117052:14"/>
hearing of it preached; and whereas our Saviour ſaith, <hi>he that beleeveth not ſhall be damned,</hi> had his intention beene, that ſuch as beleeved not ſhould be compelled thereto, doubtleſſe he would have ſaid ſo in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words upon this occaſion, rather then denounce their damnation, before he had firſt countenanced this ſo efficacious a way, as ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, for to prevent it.</p>
            <p>To ſay the Apoſtles had then no civill power, and therefore they u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">Object.</note> not, is not to the purpoſe, for if coercive power had been requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, our Saviour when he ſent them forth could as eaſily have ordered <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> them to make uſe of it (in which caſe the Magiſtrate muſt have contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted his aſſiſtance) as to ſay, <hi>heale the ſicke, clenſe leapers, raiſe the dead, and caſt out divels,</hi> and although miracles were now quite ceaſed, yet it followes not that the civill ſword is given to the Church to cleer the Goſpels paſſage, for God will have no wayes or meanes made uſe of, but ſuch as he himſelfe preſcribed with expreſſe order only (not to perſecute but) to <hi>depart from ſuch as would not heare it;</hi> and what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand finde we in the word of God which warrants us to impriſon, fine, baniſh, or put to death any one eſpecially amongſt Chriſtians for difference of opinion in Religion? many I know are ſo indulgent to be contented that every man might enjoy his own Conſcience quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but would not ſuffer them to, have the free exerciſe of it, to diſcourſe or publiſh their opinions unto others, but hereof I finde no ground in Scripture; St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 16. <hi>A command is laid upon me, and wo is unto me if I preach not the Goſpel;</hi> and our Saviour ſaid unto St. <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 22 32. <hi>When thou art converted ſtrengthen thy brethren:</hi> So that the ſame God which commands me to trie the ſpirits, requires of me alſo that when I have found the truth, I ſhould not withold it <hi>like a candle under a buſhell,</hi> but teach it unto others. <note place="margin">Marke 4. 31. <hi>Object.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Yea but ſome will ſay, God requires you to teach the Truth, but you teach Hereſie inſtead thereof, and therefore you ought to be perſecuted; my anſwer is, That I apprehend it to be the truth, and doe but diſcharge <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> my conſcience, though it be erronious, deſiring to ſee the warrant for perſecuting ſuch as teach or publiſh erronious doctrines, which they in their owne opinion thought had been ſound: St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the name of the whole Miniſtery ſaid, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. <hi>We are Ambaſſadours for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us, we pray you in Chriſts ſtead, be ye reconciled to God:</hi> And in another place, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 1. 3. 4. <hi>I Paul my ſelfe beſeech you by the meekneſſe and gentleneſſe of Chriſt, for though we walke in the fleſh, we do not war after the fleſh, for the weapons of our warfare are not carnall, but mighty through God to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds:</hi> So that <hi>Paul</hi> did war, but not according to the fleſh, he did not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117052:14"/>
fine, nor cut off eares, his weapons were only ſpirituall, the power and might of Jeſus Chriſt; gentle exhortation and friendly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition was the only meants the Apoſtles practiſed, which prevailed then ſo mightily, and ought for that very reaſon to be ſtill continued, eſpecially ſince we cannot pretend any other commiſſion but what they had, unleſſe we will alſo ſeem to have had an other Goſpel.</p>
            <p>I preſume no Proteſtant will deny, but that we are bound to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the converſion of Papiſts, Jewes, Turkes, Pagans, Hereticks, with all Infidels &amp; misbeleevers unto the only true and ſaving faith in Jeſus Chriſt, this taske how little ſoever it be practiſed and thought on, will one day lye heavy upon all Chriſtians, who are no leſſe obliged thereto in their reſpective callings, then the Apoſtles were to <hi>preach the Goſpel</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 28. 19.</note> 
               <hi>unto all Nations,</hi> as was ſaid immediately before: But as it is ſaid in the Parable, <hi>Mark</hi> 3. 27. That <hi>before one can enter into a ſtrong mans houſe and ſpoile his goods, he muſt firſt binde the ſtrong man: So before you can prevaile and reduce a Turk or Papiſt to the true reformed</hi> Religion, you muſt firſt convince him in the errours of his owne, by the evidence of Scripture, and by the power of the Holy Ghoſt, and this muſt be done by word of mouth, by writing or by both, as I rather conceive; firſt, by word of mouth, in that the Apoſtles were expreſſely ordered to go and teach all Nations, which neceſſarily inferres their preſence; and ſecondly, by writing, that it may be better diſperſed, and more freely enjoyned at all times, places and opportunities, beſides, that controverſies and buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of intricacie, are far better and more methodically ſtated and expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in writing or in Print, then can poſſibly be delivered by word of mouth: The Poet ſaid,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui volet ingenio cedere rarus erit:</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But farre more rarely ſhall you finde a man to give preheminence in point of his Religion, each thinking his owne to be the trueſt; this combat therefore muſt be ſought out upon eaven ground, on equall termes, neither ſide muſt expect to have greater liberty of ſpeech, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Printing, or whatſoever elſe, then the other: But it will be again <note place="margin">Object.</note> objected, that if ſuch a tolleration as this be granted, the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome will be quickly peſtered with a greater confuſion then that of Babel; to which I anſwer, That the confuſion will not be ſuch as is <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> ſo much imagined and feared, though it may ſeem greater at firſt then afterwards, when every man hath aſſociated himſelfe with ſuch as are of his owne opinion; and I crave leave to aske, if it be not a far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion both before God and man, and of more dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the State, and their owne ſoules, for a thouſand men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of ten ſeverall religions or opinions to aſſemble together every
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117052:15"/>
Sunday in a Pariſh Church for feare of impriſonment, fines, baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and worſe, or elſe that the ſame thouſand men and women being permitted freely, may meet in a peaceable manner at ten ſeverall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces according to their reſpective differing opinions and religion: But <note place="margin">Object.</note> you will ſay that all theſe thouſand men and women were good Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, before this licentiouſneſſe of being what they would, was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them: I anſwer, That they could not poſſibly be good Proteſtants, <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> but either were hypocrites and time ſervers, or elſe that they had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by chance, or rather by courſe of the Country into a meer formall profeſſion of the Proteſtant Religion, whereof they were not able to render a reaſon if it had been demanded, &amp; though they ſhould have ſtil continued as viſible members of the true Proteſtant Church, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated in the outward means, their actions would have been never the more accepted of the Lord whileſt they had lived, nor their perſons at the day of judgement.</p>
            <p>Secondly though this confuſion were yet greater then you imagine, I deſire to be informed, how it may be prevented without a far worſe inconvenience; firſt, in that I finde no expreſſe warrant, and leſſe then expreſſe will not be enough to abridge any man the exerciſe of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which makes him ſinne againſt his owne Conſcience, and ſo is a <hi>doing of evill at leaſt, that good may come of it, Rom.</hi> 3. 8. And ſecondly, becauſe you are commanded to teach all Nations, which is impoſſible, unleſſe you could goe and live amongſt them, which you cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably imagine or conceive, that people of different religions &amp; opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions will permit you to remaine amongſt them who hold tenets, that when you have converted a conſiderable number, you may if you ſee poſſibility of ſtrength to compaſſe it by force of fire and ſword, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the reſt to be of the ſame Religion, much leſſe will they come unto you for the ſame reaſons, as alſo in that you will not permit them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your juriſdiction to make profeſſion of their Religion, whereof they have as good opinion as you can poſſibly have of yours, and though perhaps they might be contented (not that they are doubtfull of their owne, but in hopes it may be to make a Proſelite of you, or out of an ingenious diſpoſition and deſire to comply with you, who ſeem ſo ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous of their ſalvation) to hear what you alledge, why they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come good Proteſtants, yet you cannot in reaſon expect, or in equity require, that they ſhould not have as ample priviledge as your ſelfe, to deliver their mindes freely both in ſpeech and writing.</p>
            <p>We know that in moſt Kingdoms there are ſeverall Courts of Juſtice, which having different priviledges and juriſdictions, when any man hath cauſe to commence a Suite, he firſt informes himſelfe in which he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117052:15"/>
may likelieſt finde greateſt favour of equity and juſtice, but if his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary gaine advantage, and force him to a triall in ſuch a Court, as according to the conſtitution thereof, he could not have ſo favourable triall as in another, the party thus agrieved forth with appeals from that where he was over throwne unto another, never reſting or ſubmitting; if it may be otherwiſe avoided, untill he apprehend himſelfe, to have been equally proceeded with; and yet the triall of Religion muſt ſtill be more preciſe and equitable, in that it muſt be voluntary on both ſides.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe then that a man have a controverſie with another about land, houſes, money, merchandiſe, or what ever earthly luggage elſe, of a conſiderable valuation, is any ſo ſimple as to think that ſuch a one even whileſt he is confident of his owne right and title, will give it up unto his adverſary upon entreaty, menacies, or compulſion, and that willingly? Is it not then a greater abſurdity and incongruity of ſenſe to thinke that a man ſhould reſt contented willingly to be forced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will? nay is it not a meer impoſſibility, as abſolute as the ſubſiſtance of contrarieties? can a man in one &amp; the ſame reſpect, about the ſelf ſame thing, and at ſame time too, be both willing and yet unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? can he at ſame time think he hath juſt cauſe to keep poſſeſſion of ſuch land or moveables, and yet think he ought to render up poſſeſſion of them? how much more tenacious may we juſtly preſume every man to be of his religion, which he thinks to be the only true one? and how much more backward and unwilling will every one be that makes conſcience to part from his faith, whereby he expects not ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary profit and advantage, but his wel-being and ſalvation unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity? And if being confident in mine owne Religion, I cannot poſſibly be brought to thinke otherwiſe by force, what ever violence make me profeſſe outwardly to the contrary, then will it be neceſſary to proceed by fair meanes, that all reaſons and inducements being aledged with equall liberty and freedome on both ſides, the whole controverſie may be fully ſtated and underſtood to the ſelf-conviction of hereſie and errour, which if other Nations of different Religions may not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and by that means freely declare and expreſſe the grounds where on they built their faith, how falſe ſoever they be, they cannot poſſibly be convinced thereof, but will be ſo much more hardned in their opinions, conceiving them the founder, by how much you reſtrain the publiſhing thereof, and when they ſee you intend to perſecute them, denying an equall and indifferent triall, they will be gone again with a far more prejudiciall conceit of the Proteſtant Religion then they had before, if you detaine them perforce you do contrary to St.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117052:16"/>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 15. who gave order that even <hi>the unbeleeving wife might depart, if ſhe would depart,</hi> and beſides afright all ſuch as hear of it, from ever comming to you afterwards.</p>
            <p>Thus does it appeare moſt evidently, that if you will continue your <note place="margin">Note.</note> rules and maximes of perſecution, beſides the unwarrantableneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, you cannot reaſonably conceive a poſſibility to diſcharge our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours aforeſaid Commiſſion, with ſundry other Scriptures for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of all Nations.</p>
            <p>Beſides, we finde how amongſt other directions which our Saviour gave his ſeventy Diſciples at their miſſion, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 5. 6. He bids them, That <hi>into whatſoever houſe they enter, they firſt ſay, Peace be to that houſe, and that if the ſon of peace be there, their peace ſhall reſt upon it, if not, it ſhall returne to them againe:</hi> and by this inſtruction ſurely we may obſerve, <note place="margin">Note.</note> our Saviour did not intend, that his Diſciples whileſt they went about preaching the Goſpel ſhould crie Peace, Peace, that they might more ſecurely inſtill into their Proſelites a doctrine of war and perſecution, and ſuch Chriſtian States and Churches as do ſince practiſe it, go quite oppoſite to that command of our Saviours, and his Diſciples practiſe, wherein we are ſo much more inexcuſable, in that he declared himſelfe ſo plainly, that his meaning was, the Doctrine of Peace ſhould be prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to all, and that if they and it were not received, <hi>Their peace ſhould</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Met. 10. 14. Mark 6. 11 Luke 9. 5.</note> 
               <hi>returne to them againe,</hi> and they only <hi>ſhake of the duſt from their feet as a witneſſe againſt them at the day of judgement;</hi> as if he had ſaid ſo on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, leſt they meeting with ſuch as would not receive them and their peace, ſhould be to ſeek what further courſe to take, and thinke their labour loſt, unleſſe they had compelled them to receive both whether they would or no.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding our Saviours charging his Apoſtles to <hi>teach all Nations, Matth.</hi> 28. 19. And St. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſaying, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 17. That <hi>faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the word of God;</hi> requiring <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. The Inquiſitors are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſay with the young man in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 20. <hi>All theſe things have we done:</hi> We have preached and ſuch will not heare us, ſome that heare will not beleeve us, and ſuch as beleeve us, will not live ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, <note place="margin">Object.</note> what ſhall we do with ſuch? I anſwer, this is no more then <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> foretold, when he ſaid, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 3, 4, 5. <hi>The time will come when they will not endure ſound doctrine, but after their owne luſts ſhall they beap to themſelves teachers, having itching eares, and they ſhall turne away their ears from the truth, and ſhall be turned unto fables, but watch thou in all things, endure afflictions, doe the work of an Evangeliſt, make full proofe of thy miniſtery:</hi> v. 2. <hi>Reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long ſuffering and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117052:16"/>
doctrine:</hi> This averſeneſſe to the ſaving truth which St. <hi>Paul</hi> propheſied of, was not ſo much to be diſcovered in the time of <hi>Timothy,</hi> as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in ſucceeding ages; and St. <hi>Pauls</hi> directions in that behalfe to be applied to all Miniſters ſucceſſively: To the Romans he ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14. concerning his brethren the Jews, <hi>How ſhall they beleeve in him of whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they heare without a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher?</hi> But if he had lived in theſe dayes, <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe muſt have been taught to ſay, Do you expect they ſhould goe to Church unleſſe you whip them thither? and how ſhall they beleeve unleſſe you beat it into them? This had been as eaſie for St. <hi>Paul</hi> to have preſcribed in thoſe times had it been but as good doctrine, however the practiſe of ſome Chriſtian Countries is ſo contrary to it, that more care and watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is uſed, that Inquiſitors be circumſpect and diligent to require conformity of the outward man, then that the word be ſincerely taught, or the Sacraments adminiſtred according to their due ſimplicity and purity, to the comfort and edifying of the inward man; theſe may make a great ſhew and bravery for the preſent, ſurpaſſing in number like the Nationall Church of the Jews when it was moſt populous, but being ſuch ſpurious Chriſtians chiefly as are begot by their illegall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, and not nouriſhed by the <hi>fincere milke of the word,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2. they are never like to grow up and encreaſe in godlineſſe untill they become perfect men in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Romans about meats which were lawfull to be eaten, by ſuch as beleeved they might eat them, preſcribes notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to forbeare, rather then offend a weake brother, but withall ſayes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 22, 23. <hi>Happy is he that condemneth not himſelfe in that thing which he alloweth, and he that doubteth is damned if he eateth, becauſe he eateth not of faith, for whatſoever is not of faith is ſin.</hi> And in the ſame Chapter, verſ. 5. he ſaies, <hi>One man eſteemeth one day above another, and another eſteemeth every day alike, let every man be fully perſwaded in his owne minde;</hi> according to which doctrine, a mans owne conſcience was both primarily and laſtly to be reſolved fully before he eat or dranke, whether he keep holy-daies or no, and not the Inquiſition houſe or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops court: If eating with a doubting conſcience only be ſinne, what is it in ſuch as eat contrary to their conſcience? how much greater ſin is it in ſuch as goe to Church, or are preſent at worſhipping of God in ſuch a manner as they themſelves hold to be flat Idolatry; and then how comparatively greater is their ſin that force others to doe that which damnes themſelves, ſo much againſt their owne wills and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions? But perhaps it will be objected, that they are not forced, but may chuſe whether they will come to Church or no, ſo they pay one <note place="margin">Object.</note>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117052:17"/>
third part of their revenues or ſome eaſier fine: To which I anſwer, <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> That ſuch fines, impriſonment, or leſſer puniſhments whatſoever are juſtly to be accounted force, and that in the higheſt nature, when a man will rather reſolve to hazard the loſſe of his own ſoule in going to Church with a double conſcience, according to his owne tenets and opinion, then to ſubmit to the ſaid fines, impriſonment or other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; I need ſay no more then ſuch going to Church is not of faith, but of feare, and faith comes by hearing, not by fighting.</p>
            <p>But it will be againe objected, That the Apoſtles had no power or <note place="margin">Object.</note> authority from the civill Magiſtrate to render into obedient unto their doctrine in a compulſive way, otherwiſe they would in likelihood have made uſe of it, there being no ſuch probable meanes under, heaven as ſuch imagine, to ſettle an uniformity, as fining, impriſoning, baniſhing, cutting off eares, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if they ſee fit; whereto I anſwer, That the Apoſtles preaching, baptizing, and doing miracles, were all <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> contrary to the authority and expreſſe commands of civill Magiſtrates, and if they had had but equall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from their Maſter, having gained ſuch multitudes of converts as our Saviour was fain to feed miraculouſly at one time, about five thouſand of them, all men, beſides women and children; at another time foure thouſand men, beſides women and children, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14. 24 and 15. 38. And in the Acts it is ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 41. That through <hi>Peters</hi> preaching, <hi>three thouſand ſoules were added to them in one day,</hi> we cannot juſtly thinke but having once gained ſo many Proſelites, and amongſt thoſe were ſouldiers, to take leaders and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders <note place="margin">Luke 3. 12. 14. Act. 10. in the former part.</note> off, they had through their numbers both means and reaſon, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to encourage them in adventuring to ſettle, or at leaſt to lay ſome ground-worke of their coercive diſcipline, then with ſuch boldneſſe at firſt to travell from place to place, from one City to another, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Chriſt Jeſus undauntedly, when there was not ſo much as one to countenance and backe them againſt the civill Magiſtrate, or perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the common people.</p>
            <p>Why did the Apoſtles baptiſe or teach in the name of Jeſus, being expreſſely commanded by the civill Magiſtrate to the contrary? this diſobedience and offending of the higher powers had beene a ſin in them, unleſſe our Saviour had given them expreſſe commiſſion to teach all Nations, and if coercive power had been as warrantable, and more likely means to propagate the Goſpel, the Apoſtles were as much to blame in that they did not uſe it, as they ſhould have been if they had not preached the Goſpel at all; for Chriſt that commanded them the end, muſt needs underſtand the means there to conducing to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the ſame commiſſion; neither could they be ſaid to want
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117052:17"/>
power for putting the meanes in execution, ſo long as they had the gift of working miracles: which doubtleſſe they alſo practiſed ſo often as they had the divine Oracle for warrant; and of this nature was <hi>Peters</hi> puniſhing <hi>Ananias and Saphira with ſudden death,</hi> becauſe they had <note place="margin">Acts 5. 5. 10.</note> dedicated a certain poſſeſſion unto the Lord, and afterwards ſought to rob his Saints of part thereof: <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe, Chap. 13. 11. ſtruck <hi>Elimas</hi> the forcerer blinde, becauſe <hi>he ſought to turn away Paulus Sergius the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty his heart from the faith: And his delivering of Himenous and Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto Sathan that they might learne not to blaſpheme,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 20. I ſuppoſe may be underſtood in the ſame manner. Our Saviour having occaſion to make uſe of an Aſſe that the Propheſie in <hi>Zachariah</hi> might be fulfilled, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9 9. ſent two of his Diſciples to the village <hi>Belphage</hi> to fetch one, giving them no other inſtructions, but that if any body ſaid ought unto them, they ſhould reply, <hi>That the Lord had need of it, Matth.</hi> 21. 3. Even ſo might the Apoſtles have done when they had met with obſtinate people that would not receive their Goſpel (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Jews which the Roman Magiſtrate in likelihood regarded little whether they were Jews or Chriſtians) it had been but ſending for a Centurian, or other officer of juſtice with a little ticket, that <hi>Domino opus eſt,</hi> no body ſhould have been able to reſiſt their will; as it is ſaid in the Romans, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 19. the proudeſt <hi>Pharaoh</hi> muſt have ſubmitted, and all his Subjects been willing to aſſiſt, beſides legions of Angels <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 53.</note> which would have been in readineſſe if God had pleaſed to warrant them in ſuch a courſe.</p>
            <p>And whereas in the Scripture before alledged, it is ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 2 41. That <hi>three thouſand ſoules were added to the Church that day;</hi> the Text de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares alſo, that <hi>they which gladly received the word were baptiſed,</hi> inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that they which doe not willingly receive the word, ought not to <note place="margin">Note.</note> be baptiſed, much leſſe be forceibly baptiſed, or being firſt baptiſed in their infancie when good hopes were conceived of them, be after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards compelled to receive the word, and participate in the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces when their unwillingneſſe is ſo well known, and this to be the caſe of all ſuch Chriſtians as are forced into a Religion: But how many ſouls ſoever were added to the Church at <hi>Peters</hi> preaching, <hi>Acts</hi> 2 47. and whereas it is ſaid, That <hi>the Lord added daily to the Church ſuch as ſhould be ſaved,</hi> it cannot be ſaid ſo in ſuch Countries where the Inquiſition ruleth, or people are forced to goe to Church upon penalties how ſmall ſoever, there is neither adding to the Church, nor falling from, they are one and all, all of the Church, or all out of the Church, and which of the two is likelieſt I am ſorry to conſider.</p>
            <p>What people under heaven can boaſt of an outward unity, and ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117052:18"/>
generall a uniformity as the Papiſts at this day, moſt eminently glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous if it were to be contemplated according to humane wiſdome, or beheld with the eye of fleſh? But do not Proteſtant Writers affirme of them, that they would fall into as many peeces and opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, as all other Chriſtians have in the whole world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if the yoke of their Inquiſition bondage were but broken? Nay do not all Proteſtants conclude that even ſuch a hodge podge of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity cannot be compaſſed without an Eccleſiaſticall Sovereignty? and that this Eccleſiaſticall Sovereignty hath ſuch inbred corruptions and temptations in it ſelfe as breeds a propenſity, little leſſe then unavoidably degenerating into tyranny? and that tyranny over the minde to be ſeventy ſeven times worſe, then that which civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates exerciſe upon the body or eſtate? nay muſt it not needs follow <note place="margin">Note.</note> by conſequence undeniable, that if there were as good ground in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for ſpirituall Sovereignty as there is for temporall, that this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sovereignty ought to be reduced to Monarchy, as the beſt and only government to ſettle uniformity? and would not this Pope and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Monarch upon the ſame grounds have a better claim and title to all the world, becauſe eccleſiaſticall and ſpirituall for ſooth, then any King or Emperour hath to his owne Dominions? All theſe groſſe abſurdities (which we ſo much condemne in the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the myſtery of iniquity aimes at no leſſe then all the world, their ground-worke and proceedings conclude as much, though yet it ſpeakes not plaine) will inevitably follow the endeavouring to ſettle a uniformity in the Church, or ſuch tenets as require a neceſſity of coercive power to be executed on the body or eſtate in matters meerly of Religion.</p>
            <p>Let all Church governments be but brought to a triall, fee what the Pope can ſay, Epiſcopacie, Presbyterie, or any other that ſtands for compulſive juriſdiction over goods or perſon, and though they mince it never ſo finely, ſpeake never ſo fairly, and each of them have not really in it ſelfe an equall proportion of inbred putrifaction, tending un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſpirituall tyranny, yet if they be well examined, though in their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives one may condemn the other, for their affirmatives whatſoever ſhall be alledged by any one will be acknowledged the doctrine and principles of all the reſt, and each of them for the matter, though not equally, upon moſt palpable conſequence be found tending and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring a command and dominion over the faith and conſciences of men, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſclaimed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 24. And when <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the ſons of <hi>Zebeace</hi> deſired to ſit on our Saviours right hand, and the other on his left in glory, he told them, That the Princes of <hi>the Gentiles doe exerciſe dominion over them, and they that are great exerciſe authority
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117052:18"/>
over them, but it ſhall not be ſo among you:</hi> And when he was deſired on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſpeake a powerfull word for execution of civill juriſdiction, that an inheritance might be devided rightly betwixt two brothers, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the party, ſaying, Man, who made me a judge or devider o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 13, 14. And if the Apoſtles, and their lawfull ſucceſſors in the Miniſtery, may not exerciſe dominion nor authority, what ever their minds were, their perſecution would want a ſting, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. 25, 26.</p>
            <p>God will not have men perſecuted for matter of Religion, leſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour thereof, the perſecuting of his deareſt Saints ſhould ſeeme more juſtifiable: But you will ſay, why does he then permit the civill Magiſtrates to put men to death, by which proceeding innocent and guiltleſſe perſons have often ſuffered? I anſwer, how it is true that through the iniquity of ſome Countries Lawes, and malice or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of wicked people, innocent and ſimple men have too too often been condemned and put to death: But firſt, it is abvious to every ones capacity, how the crimes and offences for which men ſuffer under civill Magiſtrates, are by moſt Nations concurrently agreed upon to deſerve death. Secondly, ſuch delinquencies are more eaſily to be proved againſt the malefactors, and in matters of difficulty, as to diſcover whether a woman had committed adultery, the Lord had appointed a miraculous way of triall, and called it <hi>The law of jealouſies, Exod.</hi> 5. 12. which was, that if the ſpirit of jealouſie had poſſeſſed the husband, the Prieſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the wife a bitter water to drinke (in ſuch manner as is related in the Story) her thigh ſhould rot, and belly burſt if ſhe were guilty, but do her no hurt at all in caſe of innocencie; from whence may be inferred, that the putting any man to death, or puniſhing by civill Magiſtrates without undeniable proofe and witneſſes, cannot be juſtified or excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without a miracle; how much more in matters of Religion, where there is no law of Gods making that commands it, and ſeldome righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous teſtimonies that can be produced to prove it? Thirdly, it lay in the malefactors power not to have committed ſuch crimes and outrages; and laſt of all, civill Magiſtrates have the Scripture for a rule what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents they may put to death, and how far they may proceed in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: but for matter of Religion it is quite otherwiſe; for firſt, no man is of opinion that another deſerves to be perſecuted and put to death, only, becauſe he is of the ſame Religion which himſelfe is of, ſince therein he ſhould condemne himſelfe: Secondly, if a man will him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, you cannot tell what Religion he is of, becauſe whatever he is driven to make profeſſion of, it is the heart that in this reſpect, either juſtifies or condemnes: Thirdly, though a man would uſe all the means which can be preſcribed him, and ſhould even himſelfe be contented.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117052:19"/>
and deſire that ſuch a Religion were the true one, yet it is not in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to thinke ſo, and conſequently to be of the ſame in heart, untill his reaſon and underſtanding be convinced thereof: And laſt of all there is no warrant for perſecution in the Scripture, if there were, we might boldly ſay, <hi>fiat juſtitia ruat Coelum,</hi> God will beare us out in whatſoever we do by his commandement, and as ſevere an account will he require at the dreadfull day of judgement, for all ſuch fining, impriſoning, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilating, and putting to death, eſpecially of his Saints, and other conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious people, as have been practiſed without it.</p>
            <p>We are bid in the Scripture to <hi>come out of the world, and ſeparate our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 18. 4. 2 Cor. 6. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſelves from the wicked, leſt we partake of their judgements,</hi> and the like; but inſtead of conforming hereunto, ſuch as will not enter into Covenant, ſuch as will not goe to Church and receive the Communion with us, we endeavour to compell them to it by pecuniary or corporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, which is as much as poſſible to withſtand and hinder ſuch a ſeparation: for inſtead of preaching unto the true Beleevers, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding unto St. <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine, that <hi>they ſhould ſeparate themſelves,</hi> and not communicate with notorious ſinners, we quite contrary turne our ſpeech and power too, towards Papiſts, Blaſphemers, Traitors, and the mixt multitude in generall, forcing them and the true Beleevers to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble and communicate together, to have one Faith, one Baptiſme, one Church, and whether it may involve us in one doome, I leave to others to determine, and at preſent only advertiſe, that, from hence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes a double inconvenience, one to our ſelves by communicating with Atheiſts, Papiſts, Traitors, Blaſphemers and Reprobates of all ſorts, from whom we are commanded by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. to <hi>turne away,</hi> whileſt we notwithſtanding force them whether they will or no, to joyne with us in the moſt ſacred Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God: the other inconvenience is to thoſe that are ſo forced, by making of them hypocrites and time ſervers, ſo much worſe then they were before, or as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 15. <hi>Two times more the children of the divell,</hi> when perhaps what they would have done of their owne good will, though erronious, might have been in part excuſed by ignorance, and a good intention, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did when he perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Church of God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. and ſo far are we from building up the myſticall body of Chriſt by compelling the perſonall preſence of Papiſts, and ſuch like, at our ſpirituall exerciſes, that it only hardens them ſo much more, and alienates their mindes ſo much futher from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrought upon, by ſuch arguments as are alledged from reaſon or from Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:117052:19"/>
In a Sermon preached before the Houſe of Commons the 27. of December, 1643. I finde theſe words. <hi>It feareth me that a great part of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Hender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pag. 18.</note> 
               <hi>the people of this land are ſtill fond of a formall ſervice, and a proud Prelacie;</hi> and yet the Covenant which apparently profeſſes a finall extirpation of them both, had found ſuch acceptance, that I beleeve there is ſcarce one man in a hundred throughout all <hi>London</hi> but hath ſubſcribed to it; however I am fully of the ſame opinion, and verily conceive that from the carriage and effect of this buſineſſe only, it may cleerly be obſerved, how eaſily multitudes of men will permit ſhipwracke to be made of their ſoules, and conſequently how incongruous and dangerous a way of proceeding it is, to joyne profit or preferment, hopes or feares, threats or force to worke upon the conſcience; for although the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant hath paſſed thus currantly, I finde notwithſtanding by diſcourſe that the greateſt part of people are little weaned from the preſent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice Booke, and wiſh better to Epiſcopacie a little reformed, I meane the rigour of it only, with ſome ſmall ſuperfluities of the Lordlineſſe, and that it ſhould ſtill remain Dioceſan, rather then Presbyteriall, or any other Church government whatſoever; but for ſuch as hold with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependencie how their ſtomacks can throughly digeſt the Covenant, I cannot any wayes imagine.</p>
            <p>I know that much is ſaid and done in many places in behalfe of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, a Nationall Church and Covenant; which things indeed carry <hi>a great ſhew of wiſdome in wil-worſhip,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 23. were it not that our Saviour told us, That <hi>in vaine they worſhip him, teaching for doctrines, the commandements of men, Matth.</hi> 15. 9.</p>
            <p>But wherefore ſuch labouring in vaine, and ſtriving againſt the ſtreame to obtaine a ſuperficies, and falſe luſtre of a Nationall Church? Doe we thinke that Gods ſalvation is alſo Nationall? Surely if the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thouſand which <hi>never bowed knee to Baal,</hi> had been in a body, <hi>Eliah</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King. 19. 18.</note> would have knowne them better; we ſee indeed that they have all the face or ſhew of Mahumetans in <hi>Turkie,</hi> Papiſts in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans in <hi>Germany,</hi> but this is the worke of man and not of God; and though the power of fleſh is ſuch to keep the purity and ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Goſpel from them; they will be ſure enough to riſe up in judgement, and with their uncircumciſed hearts, and law of nature, <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> condemne the tyranny of thoſe that kept it from them. And they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege alſo the great reformations wrought by <hi>Ataxerxes, Ezra</hi> 7. 23. (and other good Kings under the the Law) who ſaid, <hi>Whatſoever is commanded by the God of heaven, let it be diligently done for the houſe of the God of heaven;</hi> and many ſtill crie out aloud upon a reformation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or building up the myſticall Temple under the Goſpel, after the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117052:20"/>
ſame manner by fire and ſword, never remembring, that there was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe order and direction from God himſelfe concerning every thing <note place="margin">Exod. 25. 40. &amp; 26. 30. Heb. 8. 5. Exod. 27. 19.</note> about the firſt Temple, <hi>not a pin excepted,</hi> whereas many of latter times, out of greater eagerneſſe to have the worke done, then care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration to the well doing, have put their owne commandment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot inſtead of Gods, requiring judgement to be executed ſpeedily up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that diſobeyed, <hi>whether it were to death or to baniſhment, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation of goods or impriſonment,</hi> with as much confidence, as though the Prophet <hi>Ezra</hi> had purpoſely recorded it, not ſo much that God <note place="margin">Cap. 7. 26.</note> might be glorified in <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> great carefulneſſe, and juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for beautifying of his Temple, as to countenance their owne wil-worſhip and inventrons.</p>
            <p>But did God ever ſay to any Chriſtian people as he did to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17. 8. I will give <hi>unto thee and thy ſeed thy neighbours Country,</hi> whoſe inhabitants were without the Covenant of workes, for an everlaſting poſſeſſion? How much leſſe does God give thee the confiſcation of thy brothers eſtate, whom thou wilt perhaps acknowledge to be within, and canſt not poſſibly prove to be without the covenant of Grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he differs from thee in opinion, or ſome caſes of conſcience only? Did God ever ſay to Chriſtians as he did to <hi>Abraham,</hi> v. 14. <hi>The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed man-childe ſhall be cut off from his people?</hi> If Chriſtians have any command equivolent hereunto, why is it not impartially put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution? If they have not, who ſhall anſwer for ſuch as have beene perſecuted or put to death without it? But as whatſoever God hath commanded ſhould be punctually done; ſo what God hath not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, ought not to be done: the adding to in Deuteronomy, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 32. and <hi>Johns</hi> Revelation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 18. is as much forbidden, as the taking from it; and <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30 6. <hi>Adde thou not unto the words of God, leſt he reprove thee, and thou be found liar.</hi> I am confident it cannot be denied, but that the endeavouring and practice of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive power to ſway the conſcience in any kinde, is for the moſt part either expreſſively, or by undeniable conſequence quite contrary to the principall intention and letter throughout the whole Scripture, in which reſpect if there were ſome few texts or paſſages which might ſeem to colour it, yet they ought to be ſo much more deliberately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and pondered on for the honour we owe to Gods truth, and charity to our neghbour.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpel cap. 28. 20. it is ſaid, <hi>Teach them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you;</hi> But I doe not finde perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to have been expreſſely commanded in any place of the Goſpel: and whereas ſome would infer it from the words, <hi>Let all things be done</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 40.</note>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:117052:20"/>
               <hi>decently and in order,</hi> as by the coherence with the whole Chapter it appeares plainly to relate only unto the orderly proceeding &amp; behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in their aſſemblies or publick meetings; ſo it poſſibly cannot be made appear from hence, that there is, or ought to be a power to perſecute or put to death, for then this concluſion would follow, that the Church <note place="margin">Note.</note> of Corinth had commiſſion given them to put a man to death only for indecencie, or for having done any thing which was unſeemly or out of order; but this would be both a great abſurdity, injuſtice and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to affirme: againe, Let all things be done decently and in order cannot poſſibly ſignifie, or imply a power or order of fining, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and putting to death, unleſſe you will ſay, that the Apoſtles, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and all Chriſtian Churches, eſpecially that of Corinth had the ſame power, and then you muſt either ſay that there was no delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencie to proceed againſt in a coercive way, which is notoriouſly falſe, or elſe you muſt condemn them all, becauſe they did not practiſe it at any time; for as the precept or command was given to the Church and Saints of Corinth, ſo <hi>Pauls</hi> meaning and intention muſt needs be, that they of all others ſhould obſerve and practiſe it fully and punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in all things that it might have been a preſident to others: and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the commiſſion of decencie and order in all things was given <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 1. 2. Cap 9. 10. Cap. 10. 11 8.</note> unto the Church of Corinth, is plaine, ſince the whole Epiſtle is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to them particularly, and by name, but it was written for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and concerned equally all the Diſciples &amp; Churches of Chriſt, both then living, and us, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies, <hi>On whom the ends of the world are come:</hi> now it is groſſe and prepoſterous to think or ſay, that <hi>Paul</hi> gave the Church of Corinth ſuch commiſſion, that is, an order or authority to <note place="margin">Note.</note> uſe coercive power for the better prevailing that all things might be done decently and in order, becauſe he knew they wanted, and could not have the aſſiſtance of the civil Magiſtrate thereunto; and if the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive was not intended to them, much leſſe to future Churches, who have only received the ſame commiſſion after ſo many reverſions, and can not pretend that the words thereof ſhould have a different or lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſignification in our favour, then was meant unto the Corinthians, unto whom it was immediately directed; and we may well preſume that if it had ſignified a compulſive or Lordly juriſdiction, to have been put in execution by Chriſtian Churches or Common-wealths in after ages, which cannot be becauſe of ſo many abſurd conſequences which follow thereupon, yet <hi>dato &amp; non conceſſo,</hi> in ſuch caſe I ſay, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and primitive Chriſtians, though they themſelves had wanted co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive meanes and power, would not withſtanding infallibly have left ſome ground or warrant inſerted in the letter of the Goſpel, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117052:21"/>
ſucceſſively unto poſterity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for their better direction in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſuch concernment, and ſo great obſcurity in that ſenſe which is objected; but if the point be intricate or dubious, the ſafeſt way is to proceed no further then we have a precept or preſident of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our or his Apoſtles to warrant us, eſpecially in matters of ſo high a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as are the worſhip and ſervice of God Almighty, the Diſcipline of his Houſe, and tender conſciences of his deareſt Saints.</p>
            <p>In the Goſpel we meet with <hi>Biſhops, a Preſbytery, Elders, Deacons, Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Diſciples, Prophets, ſtrange tongues,</hi> and <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 12 4. 14. Tit. 1. 5. 1 Tim. 3. 8 5. 1. 7. Act 6. be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginning. Luke 10. 1 23. 1 Cor. 12. 10. Eph 4. 11, 12, 13. Rom. 12. 8</note> 
               <hi>of tongues, Elders that rule well, and labour in the Miniſtery,</hi> ſome to <hi>take care of poore widowes,</hi> others <hi>for exhortation, Paſtors, Teachers for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Saints, for the worke of the Miniſtery, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt untill we all come in the unity of the faith,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes: But what ſpirit of truth doe we ever meet with which ſaies that any of theſe were given for the corporall impriſoning, baniſhing, or putting to death the body of Chriſt, which are his Saints, as of latter times too too often hath beene practiſed? where finde wee in the Goſpel order or authority to convent, accuſe and arraigne men with power of life and death for matters of religion or opinion only? this is but traditionall, and far ſhort from being Canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icall and Chriſtian; it is true we finde here a <hi>precept</hi> for endeavouring to accompliſh a unity of faith in the Saints, or the Saints in the unity of faith, but this was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther univerſall nor nationall unity, as appeares afterwards, where he ſayes unto the ſame Epheſians, <hi>Walke not as other Gentiles walke in the vanity of their mindes,</hi> much leſſe was any conſtraint or compulſion or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <note place="margin">Verſe 17.</note> or intended to be uſed, for then both they and all other Chriſtian Churches had been bound to make all others walke with them in unity of faith, or to walke unto the gallowes; and the Apoſtles admonition in ſuch caſe would have been both more proper and effectuall which the Epheſians, as ſuch Church commanders pretend, if he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid, Walke not as other Gentiles, who becauſe they will not walke with you in unity of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ligion, and uniformity of diſcipline, are deſervedly compelled to walke unto the gallowes.</p>
            <p>Hath it not often been inſtilled into the eares of Princes, as <hi>Hansan</hi> the great favourite did unto King <hi>Ahaſue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> concerning the Jewes Gods people, who were then afflicted in captiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bjectly contemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>le, that they could not poſſibly be dangerous to the State? and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proud <hi>Haman, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtner</hi> 3. 8, 9. &amp;c. only becauſe a conſciencious <hi>Mordecai</hi> was ſcrupulous and could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow and doe rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ience to him as the King commanded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ed h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>jeſty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>a there was <hi>a certaine peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcattered ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ſperſed into all Provinces of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117052:21"/>
whoſe lawes were divers from all people, neither kept they the Kings lawes, and therefore it was not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them;</hi> in which reſpect, if it pleaſed his Majeſty that letters might be writ for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>he promiſed to pay ten thouſand talents of ſilver into the Kings treaſurie;</hi> hereupon the King con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ented to the Edict, that <hi>all of them men, women and children ſhould be maſſacred,</hi> and for <hi>Hamans</hi> good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, remitted the ten thouſand talents of ſilver, and gave him the poore Jews to boot, to be murdered in ſuch a manner as his cruelty could b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rive: Oh how often hath this wicked advice of <hi>Haman</hi> been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed upon Gods beſt people in all parts of Chriſtendome? for there are Puritanes both in <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> in greater numbers then ever appeared in <hi>England</hi> before this preſent Parliament, and permitted to meet and walke peaceably up and downe the ſtreets together, more numerous then ever yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaw in <hi>London,</hi> may it, in Gods time, be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the greater humbling, then ſhame of this Nation and all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants beſides.</p>
            <p>But how often thinke we may it have been ſuggeſted unto our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sovereignes, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>nuated unto the people, how diſſerviceable and dangerous the Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itanes were unto the State? ſurely not ſeldome, or elſe they would never have reduced ſo many thouſands of them into a neceſſity of leaving the Land, and carry with them their gifts, arts, and manufactures into other Countries, to the greateſt detriment of this Common-wealth; and yet far greater loſſe and judgement unto Gods Church in <hi>England:</hi> But what hath been the end of the grand Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians and Perſecuters? may it not be obſerved, that like <hi>Haman</hi> who was hanged on the gallowes, which he himſelfe had cauſed to be ſet up for <hi>Morde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai,</hi> ſo many, nay, very many of the greateſt that ever yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared enemies unto Gods people, have been taken in their own nets, and felt thoſe penalties and proceedings, which they firſt invented and practiſed upon others? And as that villanous deſigne of <hi>Hamans, Eſt.</hi> 8. 8. through Gods providence proved ſo much more ſucceſſefull unto the Jewes; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in like manner may the ſun-ſhine of Gods love have beene ſeene to breake out ſtill more bright and comfortable towards ſuch as in all times have been reproached for Puritanes, I may not ſay for any deſerts or works of theirs, but through Gods moſt gracious providence, which as <hi>Mordecai</hi> foretold to <hi>Eſther,</hi> cap. 4. 14. hath wrought enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and deliverance to them, though they perhaps may be ſaid to have endeavoured it, not without many weakneſſes and failings.</p>
            <p>But ſince God both can and will finiſh his owne great work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in ſpight of all oppoſition, <hi>Let ſuch as thinke they ſtand take</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 12. <hi>Note.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leſt they fall,</hi> and may it be far from any of Gods good ſervants to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117052:22"/>
imagine that God delivered them out of perſecution to the end they might be inabled to perſecute their brethren: Perſecution is a ſinne, <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 28, 29.</note> a ſigne of the Church malignant, and no degree thereof diſpenſable by Popery, Epiſcopacie, or Presbytery, neither may God be thought to be the author of it, or countenance it further then he doth other ſinnes by barely permitting them in wrath and judgement to chaſtife and ſcourge a ſinfull people, the whole Kingdome did acknowledge it whileſt Popery domineered, the greateſt part are weary of it in Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; O let Presbytery be forewarned thereby, and know that they have the ſame temptation which was common to both the other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and wherein they miſcarried. The Jewes came out with <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 13.</note> ſwords and ſtaves to apprehend our Saviour, but God never bleſſed them in it, nor ſanctified them ſince to bring men in, and made profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Goſpel. Let all the reaſons, grounds and principles for a coercive power and diſcipline in matter of Religion be produced, and it will moſt evidently appeare how Presbytery cannot poſſibly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge more, or better then what the Papacie and Prelacie firſt brought to light, all having the ſelf ſame inbred matter and corruption in them, which infallibly, though not with equal poſting, inclines them natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to degenerate into tyranny &amp; perſecution, and the work which they all fight againſt, being of God, <hi>cannot poſſibly be overthrowne,</hi> but will notwithſtanding be brought about to the greater miſery and confuſion <note place="margin">Act. 5. 39.</note> of all ſuch, who if they would make ſtrickt enquiry with an upright heart into the nature of ſuch government, could not likely chuſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving felt or underſtood the bondage which this Kingdome hath already twice ſuffered under it, but ſee the malignant poyſon and putrifaction which is bred and lyes lurking within the bowells thereof, and be weary of it; yet I forbeare to judge, and in all meekneſſe beſeech that they would be as backwards in judging others.</p>
            <p>The Italians have a Proverbe that whoſoever goes beyond his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion muſt run the hazard of it for his owne account; but for ſuch who have no commiſſion at all, and yet take away the liberty, liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, limbs and lives of their Chriſtian brethren, and that for meere matter of conſcience only, cannot amount to leſſe then the ſhedding of innocent blould, that crying ſinne, for which the Jewes remain ſtill ſcattered upon the face of the earth untill this day: But have the Jews been thus afflicted for putting Chriſt to death, and a few of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets only, how exceſſive then will be the torments of ſuch Chriſtian States which have perſecuted and put to death thouſands of Chriſtians for every ſingle ſoule which was executed by the Jews, and that prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally becauſe ſuch Chriſtians differed from them onely in opinion,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117052:22"/>
when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f they had been Turkes or Pagans they might likely have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped? But you will ſay perhaps, that the Jews put Chriſt to death the <note place="margin">Object. Anſw.</note> ranſome and Saviour of the whole world: I anſwer, That they knew him not to be Chriſt, and that the Jewes had then better grounds and warrant to <hi>put a blaſphemer to death,</hi> and <hi>ſuch they ccounted Jeſus,</hi> then <note place="margin">Lev. 24. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Matth. 26. 65. Gen. 45. 3. 5. Math. 26. 53, 54, 56.</note> Chriſtians have now: Secondly. I anſwer, That when <hi>Joſeph</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that his brethren were troubled in minde and grieved for having ſold him into ſlavery, making himſelfe knowne, bid them not be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or angry with themſelves, for that <hi>God hand ſent him before into Egypt to preſerve their lives:</hi> and cur Saviour after they had laid hands on him, and apprehending him, for the comfort no doubt of repentant Jewes, was pleaſed ſo ſay, That if he had prayed, <hi>his Father could have given him more then twelve legions of Angels, but then the Scriptures would not have been fulfilled, that it muſt be ſo,</hi> and that <hi>all was done that the Scriptures of the Prophets might be fulfilled.</hi> In <hi>John</hi> we finde that <hi>therefore they could not beleeve becauſe Eſaias ſaith, He hath blinded their eyes, Joh.</hi> 12. 39. 40. And whereas the ſame Evangeliſt ſaith, 1 <hi>John 4. 20. He that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen, how ſhall he love God whom he hath not ſeen:</hi> So the Jews, though they ſaw Jeſus and crucified him, yet they knew him not to be God, and by <hi>Johns</hi> way of arguing, were ſo much more to be excuſed, and the ſinne of Chriſtians aggravated, who doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know their brethren, but many times acknowledge that they ſetting aſide the difference of opinion, have more eminent gifts and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties then themſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet will not forbeare to perplex and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them, and according to the principles which many of them hold and practiſe, had they been living in our Saviours dayes, they would <note place="margin">Note.</note> have been far likelier to have crucified him, then were the Jews them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And who can reſlve me, whether the penitent thiefe was not once guilty, and actually conſenting unto Chriſts death? or whether ſuch Chriſtians as come ſhort in nothing, but that they have not Chriſt on earth in their power, will not be one day found guilty or crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him againe, though they could not act it upon his perſon: beſides the Saints are <hi>coheir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s with Chriſt,</hi> they are <hi>his beloved ones, his glory, his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 17 R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v. 2. 9. Pſi. 108. 6 Eph 1. 23. 1 Cor. 12. 12. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 105. 15 2 Cor. 8 23 Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſpouſe,</hi> nay they are <hi>his body,</hi> they are <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, they are all <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ointed</hi> of the Lord, and we are forbid to <hi>touch them:</hi> Oh let us not be longer guilty of perſecuting the leaſt of them: And whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eas Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted the Hebrewes that they ſhould not be forgetfull to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine ſtrangers,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſome thereby had entertained Angels unawares;</hi> I humbly wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h all Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtian people would, in the feare of God, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whether in putting their Chriſtian brethren to death for matters of conſcience &amp; Religion only, they do not run a thouſand times greater
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117052:23"/>
hazard to ſpill the innocent bloud of Gods choſen people, his <hi>firſt born; whoſe names are written in heaven,</hi> and that it be imputed to them to have <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 23.</note> crucified the Lord himſelfe againe, far more wilfully then the Jewes, becauſe <hi>we crucifie him in his Saints,</hi> our brethren, <hi>whom we have both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and knowne.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 40. 45.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid in the Acts, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 12, 13, 14, 16. that when <hi>Gallio</hi> was Deputy of <hi>Achaia,</hi> the Jewes made inſurrection with one accord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Paul,</hi> and brought him to the judgement feat, ſaying, This fellow <hi>perwadeth men to worſhip God contrary to the Law,</hi> but <hi>Gaellio</hi> anſwered the Jews, and told them, <hi>if it were a matter of wrong or wicked lewdneſſe,</hi> he would have done as equity required, and herewith drove them from the judgement ſeat: now though no doubt but God guided this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of <hi>Gallio,</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> might have the better opportunity to preach the Goſpel, ſo is <hi>Gallio</hi> his judgement more remarkable, who at ſuch a time and inſtant, as God had over him a ſpeciall, and more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary providence could ſay, (though it is likely that he regarded alike the Jewiſh and the Chriſtian Religion, yet we who are under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel may eſpecially learne it from him) that the worſhiping of God in a <note place="margin">Note.</note> different manner, though contrary to an eſtabliſhed civill Law, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as men finde themſelves bound in conſcience, which muſt not be wavering or doubting, ought not to be interpreted or accounted as wicked lewdneſſe, or a matter of wrong to thoſe that were of another opinion, much leſſe be puniſhed as ſuch.</p>
            <p>The paſſage of <hi>Gamaliel, Act.</hi> cap. 5. and what he ſaid to diſſwade the Jewes from perſecuting the Apoſtles to death, is no leſſe worth our ſerious conſideration: The Apoſtles having cured and converted mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of people, verſ. 18. the high Prieſt and all that were with him being full of indignation, laid hands on the Apoſtles and put them into priſon, but the Lord who never forſakes thoſe that truſt in him, ſent an Angel and brought them out againe; the Apoſtles according as the Angel bid them, went into the Temple to reach the word of life, which when the Jewes underſtood, they cauſed them to be apprehended and brought before the Councell that they might be put to death: The Jewes having finiſhed their accuſations, and the Apoſtles anſwered what God inſpired them with for their owne defence, <hi>Gamaliel</hi> one of the Councell, a Phariſie, a great Doctor of the Law, and in reputation among the people, having commanded the Apoſtles to withdraw, ſaid unto them, verſ. 35. Ye men of Iſrael, <hi>take heed to your ſelves what ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to doe concerning theſe men,</hi> and having given examples of <hi>Theudas</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> who for a while drawing much people to them, were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards diſperſed, exhorted them to <hi>let the Apoſtles alone,</hi> ſaying, v. 38. 39.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117052:23"/>
               <hi>if this counſell or this worke be of God, ye cannot overthrow is,</hi> leſt happily yt be found even to fight againſt God; and the Jewes agreed with him: I know that moſt men now adayes, either reflect little upon theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, or account both <hi>Gamaliel</hi> and <hi>Gallio</hi> to have plaid the worldly polititians in this buſineſſe, and not being ſervent in their owne Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tooke care only to quiet the people for the preſent, alledging, that we muſt not live like thoſe that ſay, let the world goe how it liſt, nor <note place="margin">Object.</note> expect that God will relieve us when we dye ſtill in the ditch, and cry God helpe ut only; but I deſire ſuch to conſider, that as the luke-warm are ſo diſtaſtefull unto God, that he hath declared himſelfe <hi>to ſpue them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Rev. 3. 16. Rom. 10. 2 Jam. 2. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>out;</hi> ſo he hath alſo ſaid, that men many times have <hi>a zeale without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and that <hi>the wrath of man workes not the righteouſneſſe of God,</hi> for which cauſe <hi>James</hi> exhorts them to <hi>be ſlow to wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gamaliel</hi> and <hi>Gallio</hi> are not to be looked upon barely as polititians, who in that reſpect might be biaſed, &amp; carried away through their own private intereſt, or that of State, but their reaſon ſhould be truly valued by men of moderate temper, not without zeale, the more the better ſo it be <hi>according to knowledge,</hi> but I mean ſuch men as are not engaged to <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 2</note> the contrary opinion: <hi>Gamaliels</hi> great argument was, that the Jewes ſhould forbeare to perſecute the Apoſtles, becauſe they ran a hazard of <note place="margin">Note.</note> fighting againſt God, and this was no bare jealouſie or phanſie of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliele,</hi> but a moſt ſacred truth; for we finde that our Saviour told <hi>Paul</hi> before he was converted, that he perſecuted him, whileſt he held the garments of thoſe that ſtoned <hi>Steven,</hi> and haled the Saints both men and women up and downe before Magiſtrates and into priſon. <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 4, 5. and 22. and 23. chap. And it is yet further to be obſerved that theſe advices and counſells of <hi>Gallio</hi> and <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> were not only grounded upon policie, reaſon and Religion, but were in favour of the Apoſtles, and recorded by the Spirit of God, with the liberty and ſucceſſe which enſued thereon in the Apoſtles freer preaching of the Goſpell, which in a kinde of ſilent manner tells us they were guided by an eſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to become inſtruments of procuring Liberty of Conſcience unto the Apoſtles, and remaine an example for all Chriſtians to grant the ſike to one another.</p>
            <p>Will it not be acknowledged that the Biſhops in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, and ſince, perſecuted many Chriſtians, and therein reſiſted Chriſt inſtead of ſetting him up upon his throne? Yea ſome will ſay, but they <note place="margin">Object.</note> were Papiſts in Q. <hi>Marie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> dayes, and Epiſcopacie is <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> but <hi>Preſbytery</hi> or ſome other government may be <hi>jure divino,</hi> and will only ſuppreſſe Hereſies, and ſettle a uniformity in the Church of Chriſt: I anſwer, that the Biſhops in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, and ſince, whether <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:117052:24"/>
Papiſts or others, did then ſay as much, and with equall confidence in defence of their coercive proceedings for preventing Schifines, and eſtabliſhing uniformity, and, that they had Gods word to backe them in it, and though I am fully aſſured, that God hath been pleaſed to dif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unto us ſince, a greater meaſure of his truth then ever, yet if a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, or other Eccleſiaſticall government ſhall ſilence or perſecute in whatſoever manner, ſuch Chriſtians as are conſcientious, pious in their actions, zealous for God, and painfull in propagating of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, though they differ in opinion, and hold ſome points contrary to the current of the times, but are obedient to higher powers in civil matters that ſuch ſhould be perſecuted whether by Presbyteriall or other go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, I never yet heard other reaſon for it then what Antichriſt himſelfe alledged ſo long ſince, nor doe ſee any other likelihood from the politick conſtitution of this State, much leſſe can finde evidence in Scripture, but it may run the hazard, that future times, when God ſhall pleaſe to enlighten us yet further, will acknowledge it to be erronious, that it will appear in the laſt day to have been <hi>a fighting againſt God,</hi> and <hi>perſecuting of Chriſt,</hi> or at leaſt a reſiſting and <hi>quenching of the Spirit and gifts of God,</hi> which are acknowledged to be in ſuch men ſo ſilenced and oppoſed.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Corinthians tells them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, in the beginning, There are <hi>diverſities of gifts</hi> but <hi>one Spirit one Lord one Gods to one,</hi> he ſaies, <hi>is given the word of wiſdom, to an other the word of knowledged</hi> to one <hi>faith,</hi> and an other the <hi>gift of healing;</hi> to one the <hi>gift of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to an other <hi>propheſie;</hi> to one <hi>diſcerning of ſpirits,</hi> to an other <hi>divers kinde of tongues,</hi> and to an other the <hi>interpretation of tongues,</hi> but <hi>all theſe work by one and the ſelfe ſame Spirit.</hi> And though all theſe are gifts of the Spirit and that there is not any one of theſe but a man may have it, and be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, for even of faith <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſaies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> though he had it in ſuch a degree as he could remove mountaines if he had not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity withall, he were nothing, yet it is ſaid in the 7 verſe of the 12. Chaper, That <hi>the manifeſtation of the Spirit in the diverſity of gifts, is given to profit with;</hi> that is for the profit, and benefit of the Church to which theſe gifts were to be communicated: now if all theſe gifts are from God, and if God gave them that they might be improved or diſpenced unto all Nations; nay, ſince in the third verſe of the ſame Chapter, it is revealed unto us, that no man can ſo much as ſay, That <hi>Jeſus is the Lord but by the holy Ghoſt:</hi> how can it be denied, but that the ſilencing or perſecuting of any man that hath but one or more of theſe gifts in him, <note place="margin">Note.</note> becauſe he wants ſome others, or hath not all, is not a plaine ſuppreſſing of the Holy Ghoſt? which though given in a ſmaller meaſure (like him
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117052:24"/>
that had but one talent in the Goſpel, and was condemned to utter <note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> darkneſſe for not imploying it) or if it had extended only to the ſaying that Jeſus is the Lord, were all given to profit by, and would doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe effectually prove profitable, if they were not unwarrantably quenched.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe I were of the faith generally profeſſed in New <hi>England,</hi> and had a brother of the Presbyteriall Diſcipline in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who loving me as himſelfe, deſired nothing ſo much as to conforme me to his own opinion, I that ammo whit inferiour to him in affection, that I may bee the better able to give account of my owne faith, free from the leaſt doubting, but prepared to imbrace any truth which to me remains yet unrevealed, after I have tried it by the touch ſtone of Gods word, and made uſe of ſuch other helpes as God hath given me, that I may be the ſtronger ſetled, and not ſeem obſtinate in my opinion, but eſpecially hoping hereby, as St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9. 22. whileſt he became <hi>all things to all men,</hi> to convince my brother in the errour of his wayes, I render my ſelfe complying upon his requeſt, to heare or read whatſoever can bee ſaid in the defence of Presbytery: Now when I have uſed all thoſe lawfull meanes which he preſcribed me, or could thinke any waves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable to reduce a man to: that opinion, and tell him notwithſtanding, that I finde not the leaſt, ſcruple or ground of doubting in that faith which before I made profeſſion of; my brother, who ſees no greater errour or weakneſſe in me then in himſelfe, hath nothing elſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt me, knowes that I cannot be of what religion or opinion I will my ſelfe, untill I be fully convinced about the truth there of, and that a bare doubting in point of conſcience, would bring damnation on me, can I ſay, my brother Presbyter in ſuch a caſe, upon good, ground or reaſon, thinke I ought to be ſilenced or perſecuted in any, manner? Can there be a Law according to Gods word to punish me for what lay not in my power to remedy nor may with a ſafe conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be diſſembled? But it will be ſaid, that this plyableneſſe and <note place="margin">Object.</note> readineſſe to receive ſuch truth as ſhall be diſcovered, may be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet and hypocriticall, and that ſuch as Scripture and reaſon doe not convince, are wilfully obſtinate, or inſtate of reprobation, though they, know it not themſelves: To this I anſwer, That though it be ſaid of <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> the Jewes, This people is waxed groſſe, and their cares are dull of; hearing, <hi>and their eyes have they cloſed, leſt they ſhould ſee with their eyes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 28. 27.</note> 
               <hi>and heare with their eares, and under ſtand with their heart, and ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,</hi> and I ſhould heale them, yet it was not meant that every one of that Nation was hardned, or of any particular perſon that he could bee diſtinguiſhed from the reſt, nay it is plaine, there are no ſignes or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117052:25"/>
given us infallibly to know an obſtinate or reprobate heart by, for though it be ſaid, <hi>A good tree doth not bring forth bad fruit,</hi> &amp; <hi>you ſhall know</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 43, 44. Act 22.</note> 
               <hi>the tree by the fruit,</hi> and that <hi>of thornes men do not gather figs, nor of bramble buſhes grapes;</hi> yet we know that <hi>Paul</hi> perſecuted, &amp; was a blaſphemer to the laſt, even till he was vocally called by Chriſt from heaven; and the ſame Chriſt when he was on earth ſaid, <hi>No man can come unto me except</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 6. 44.</note> 
               <hi>the Father draw him,</hi> and therefore we have expreſſe order to <hi>judge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before the time,</hi> untill the Lord come who will bring to light the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 5.</note> hidden things of darkneſſe; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 4. <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt an other mans ſervant, to his owne maſter he ſtandeth or falleth, yea he ſhall be upheld, for God is able to make him ſtand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We finde in <hi>Matthew, Matth.</hi> 17. 5. that the Apoſtles heard a voice from heaven, ſaying, This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed, heare ye him: And our Saviour bid them <hi>tell no body thereof till he was riſen again from the dead:</hi> whence we may be informed, that <hi>Hear ye him,</hi> was not ſaid ſo much to the Apoſtles themſelves, as to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in their generations to the end of the world; for if that viſion, and that doctrine of <hi>Heare ye Chriſt;</hi> be not to be taught till after our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our be riſen from the dead, after which time he had but a few dayes to ſpend amongſt them on earth, then muſt it follow, That it is Chriſt ſtill that ſpeaks to us in his Goſpel, and by the Miniſters of his Goſpel, the power which the Miniſters of the Church have, is the power of Chriſt, who is the head of the Church, and though Chriſt as he is God, hath power equall with God, and all power was given unto him in <note place="margin">Matth; 28, 18. Joh. 18, 36</note> Heaven and in Earth; yet as he ſaid his Kingdom was not of this world, ſo neither may the Church imploy the power of the world, or uſe ſuch coercive meanes in the government of his Kingdome, as men be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to performe outward obedience for feare, and doe what they doe for the Church or civill powers ſake, and not for Chriſts, like unto thoſe people who are led to worſhip the Divell, leſt he ſhould doe them hurt.</p>
            <p>And as in a politicke State, it is not ſafe to ſuffer a penny to be taken or forced from any man in an illegall way; ſo much leſſe may an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall government and power, or the Church of Chriſt extend their juriſdiction beyond the expreſſe and preciſe warrant of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Law, for Chriſts power being unlimited as he was God and Man, whoſoever layes claim thereunto to exerciſe it according to any other rule, ſubjects himſelf to the greateſt temptation of becomming a bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Tyrant, and the people to be enthralled by the moſt arbitrary and wretched tyranny and vaſſallage of any under heaven: 1. Becauſe they that take upon them this ſupremacie of expounding Scripture
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117052:25"/>
whether in doctrine or diſcipline muſt ſay in effect, or infer by their proceedings, that their dictates are the infallible truths of God, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe men will be apt to think they had as good beleeve their own: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that it is infallibly Gods wil to have thoſe dictates of theirs to be forced upon mens conſciences: and thirdly, that they are infallibly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thereunto, &amp; guided by Gods Spirit to ſee them executed; all which are the darling reaſons and tenets of the Papacie to uphold the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Scepter, greater they cannot be, the very Power and Spirit of God himſelfe; as they pretend, and leſſe would not be colour enough to force the people to receive them: Now I ſhall leave it to every underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chriſtian to thinke and judge, whether ſuch as exerciſe the ſame <note place="margin">Note.</note> dominion and power over the conſcience which the Pope does, and not give the ſame, or as good a reaſon for it, may not be thought greater tyrants and uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pers in requiting ſuch obedience and implicite faith to their owne abilities and ſtrength, which the Pope is ſo modeſt as to acknowledge only due to an infallibility, and that infallibility to be from God?</p>
            <p>In civill affaires we ſee by experience that every man moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtands beſt his owne buſineſſe, and ſuch as doe not, but rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the managing and furelight of others, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they of what calling or condition ſoever, in a few yeares run out at heels to the utter undoing of themſelves and whole families; beſides we ſhould thinke it a moſt groſſe ſoleciſme, and extravagant, courſe in any State which did make Laws and Statutes, that the Subject might not goe about and diſpatch his worldly buſineſſe, ſave in one generall preſcript forme and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as a thing moſt irrationall and inequitable, becauſe it cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be ſutable to the infinite occaſions and intereſts of a Kingdome, or leſſer people: Nay, why are not all <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> thus manacled, if <hi>Divinity</hi> may be ſo much improved thereby? why have not each of them their reſpective theſes, poſitions, and concluſions limited and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned them? why are Phyſitians permitted to make experiments, and kill men after what faſhion they pleaſe? Surely this kinde of <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Government</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> ſhould firſt have practiſed upon other <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> without daring to tamper with <hi>Theologie</hi> and <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> before it had proceeded maſter of all the reſt: Beſides, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in the Parable, where the more early labourers murmured, that the latter commers ſhould have equall reward with them, ſaid, <hi>Is it not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me to do what I will with mine own?</hi> So we know that every man is <note place="margin">Matth. 20 15.</note> deſirous to doe with his owne as he thinks good himſelfe, (eſpecially when others receive no wrong thereby, as in the ſaid Parable) and if it <note place="margin">Ver. 13.</note> thrive not in his owne way, he may thanke himſelfe, and will like bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117052:26"/>
of it, and be content with what he does himſelfe though it prove ill not ſo, if others have the manage and ordering of it againſt his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: but in ſpirituall matters it holdeth much ſtronger, and concernes men to be more circumſpect and warie, as the good or ill there of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth unto eternity: wherefore ſince it is as poſſible for them or him to erre, who take upon them to conduct me to heaven, as I my ſelfe, ſince it is granted that <hi>I muſt give account, repent and beleeve for my ſelfe,</hi> and <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 12. 1 Cor. 2. 11.</note> cannot doe either by proxie; ſince <hi>no man knoweth the things of a man, ſave the ſpirit of the ſame man which is within him;</hi> ſince my ſalvation ought to be more deare unto my ſelfe then to any elſe; ſince if I miſcarry through mine owne choice and will, I ſhall eaſier acknowledge my deſtruction to be from my ſelfe, and declare Gods judgements to be juſt; If I periſh by mine own folly, tis the loſſe of one, but if miſled by others, we all fall into the ditch together, with an aggravation of our condemnation, to me that relyed finally upon others in a buſineſſe of the greateſt concernment that poſſibly could befall me, without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſſibility or aſlurance of doing well, than by an implicite faith; and to them that tooke upon them to be guide and pilote unto others in a coercive way eſpecially, when they knew not how to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For all theſe reſpects, and infinite others which might be heaped up, I deſire every Chriſtian heart, in the feare of God, to conſider, and revolve in his ſaddeſt and moſt retired thoughts, whether it be not a much ſafer way in ſpirituall affaires, for every particular man to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his owne eſtate betwixt God and himſelfe, and manage his own buſines; whether it be not a greater infringement of Chriſtian libertie and proprietie, to have burdens and impoſitions layd upon the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <note place="margin">Note.</note> whereby a poore ſoule lives in hatefull bondage upon earth, and ſubjects it ſelfe unto perpetuall torments in hell hereafter, without a meanes or poſſibility to helpe himſelfe, though he be ſenſible of the miſerable ſtate and condition wherein he is, or apprehend the inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deſtruction whereto they lead him?</p>
            <p>If the redeeming civill rights and priviledges which hath made this preſent Parliament ſo deare, be acceptable in ſo high a nature as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the Kingdome in a war for their defence; how much more will the Liberty of Conſcience, which tranſcends the other, as far as ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall liberty does temporall, engage it ſtill further at their devotions? The civill Lawes permit Subjects to defend their eſtates with Swords and Guns; but what kinde of Laws are thoſe which expoſe men na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, to have their Religion and Conſciences aſſaulted? The civility of the French Nation is ſuch, that in regard the Proteſtants, though they have a liberty of profeſſion, being moſt commonly fewer in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117052:26"/>
in what ever company they happen, leſt the Proteſtants ſhould there with be adaſh'd as wanting courage, and not enjoy an equall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and freedome of converſation with the Papiſts; in this reſpect; they are ſo temperate and diſcreet, that it is held an inſeemly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civill part, for a Papiſt to aske an other what Religion he is of; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in <hi>England</hi> it is ordinary with Proteſtants, to reproach one another with the nick-name of Puritan or Separatiſt, Presbyterian or Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, even thoſe which we cannot but acknowledge to be conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and jealous of offending God in any thing, and that which renders us inexcuſable, is, that many times when we cannot colourably fix any of theſe diſtinctions upon a man, who differs from us in opinion, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe only, we are ſo apt to terme him malignant or Popiſhly affected, though never any Law was yet made to declare them ſuch.</p>
            <p>It is uſuall with gameſters to ſay they had rather loſe their own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, then that others ſhould loſe it for them; and ſurely if we took as much delight in ſaving our ſoules, as gameſters doe in loſing of their money, we would quickly chuſe to hazard the loſſe of our owne ſouls our ſelves, rather then forgoe the preſent joy and comfort of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the ſalvation of them by our owne, and not by an implicite faith.</p>
            <p>Parents or ſuch as beare affection, when God pleaſes to call their friends or children out of this world by ſickneſſe, have great content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they were neare at hand to ſend for the Phyſitians, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide ſuch remedies, as if God had pleaſed, were likelieſt to prevail for their recovery; how much more then will it encreaſe the miſeries of the damned, when they ſhall thinke and ſee how fooliſh and ſottiſh they have been, to take no care or thought of making their ſalvation ſure, by trying of the ſpirits, and ſearching whether they were in the truth or no? How will children curſe their parents; ſervants their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and whole Nations the State and Government wherein they were borne and bred, which inſtead of teaching them to <hi>prove all things and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 21.</note> 
               <hi>hold faſt that which is good,</hi> have brought them up in blinde devotion, and ſuperſtitious idolizing of whatſoever their anceſtors or themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, ſaying, they ought to be wiſe unto ſobriety, and not preferre their owne ſtudies or judgements, before the Acts and Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods and whole Kingdomes? It is true that Chriſt promiſed he would ſend <hi>the Spirit which ſhould lead them into all truth,</hi> and that <hi>where two or</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 16. 7. 13. Matth. 18. 20.</note> 
               <hi>three be gathered together in his name he will be in the midſt of them,</hi> from whence, and ſuch like Scriptures it will follow; that a Church, Synod or Councell cannot erre in fundamentalls, no more then elect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian fall finally from grace; ſo long as ſuch a Synod, or Church keeps
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117052:27"/>
cloſe unto the Scriptures, and herein all Chriſtians agree, and joyne in one confeſſion, that the Bible is the very truth and word of God, but when a Proteſtant Synod or Papall Councell ſhall goe further, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe, make Inferences, Conſequences. Concluſions, Canors, and the like; or ſay, this is the genuine, full and only ſenſe and meaning of ſuch a Text, and not as their reſpective adverſaries object, herein they are both, though not equally, in a poſſibility offerring, and cannot be infallibly ſure of truth, but as each of them is ant to abound in their own ſenſe, thinking their peculiar expoſition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it, and cannot chuſe but be ſwayed there with, ſo ought they equally, to leave all ſuch as differ from them, as large a liberty and freedome to enjoy their owne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for though the Members of one Synod may be more learned, wiſe, and outwardly conſcientious, and zealous in Religion then another, yet theſe are no infallible grounds, and tokens of Gods greater illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and preſence with one then with the other, and though a third and more ſuperiour Synod, ſhould ſee that one of the two former is in an errour, and adviſe them that they ſhall do well to aſſent unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet this Synod which hath two to one againſt it ſelfe, neither may, not can forſake their owne opinions, upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate authority of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, before they ſee cleare evidence in Scripture, whereby their owne reaſon findes it ſelfe convinced: And ſince in that text accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt afore mentioned, where it is ſaid, cap. 16. 13, 14, 15. <hi>The Spirit ſhall lead them into all truth;</hi> it appears, that, that truth is no other, then what the bleſſed Spirit had heard and received of Chriſts, then much leſſe may frail mankinde whether aſſembled in a Synod, or otherwiſe, thinke any thing of their owne addition, or but varied in the leaſt tittle, to be infallible, or of equall authority with Scripture: nay, ſince neither Chriſt, nor his Diſciples thought good to force men to receive their Goſpel, how much more preſumptuous is it in men of the ſame paſſions and infirmities with others, to impoſe Cannons and reſolutions upon the conſciences of their brethren?</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſaid unto his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 6. <hi>Give not that which is holy unto dogs, neither caſt your pearles before ſwine leſt they trample them under their feet:</hi> and when a woman of Canaan be ſought him, unto whom upon the third motion, he anſwered, cap. 15. 26, 28. <hi>O woman great is thy faith;</hi> yet upon her firſt and ſecond deprecation, ſhe could obtaine no better anſwer, then, <hi>It is not meet to take the childrens bread, and caſt it unto dogs:</hi> And in <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 16, 17. God ſaid unto the wicked, <hi>What haſt thou to doe to take my Covenant into thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteſt my wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s behinde thee?</hi> Yet theſe Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors and Inquiſitons, which compell others to communion with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117052:27"/>
them, doe not barely proſtitute the ſacred Ordinances of God, by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>cing and alluring a mixt multitude to abuſe them, but far more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o naturally, and with greater impiety, becauſe ſpirituall, then thoſe of Sodome tempt provoke and force them by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ny ſeverall wayes, to raviſh and deflowre the Church their ſpirituall Mother, and deareſt Spouſe of Chriſt: Nay, ſuppoſe Chriſt Jeſus himſelfe ſhould come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine perſonally, and llive amongſt us upon earth, I would very ſaine be aſſured, how he might be free of being perſocuted, and crucified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, according to the principalls of ſuch government, if he ſhould either worke miracles, or teach, or ſpeake any thing beſides the rule of mans inventions, or above the capacity of our fraile and carnall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions.</p>
            <p>It is acknowledged that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject unto the higher powers;</hi> but this only is meant in civill matters, and not ſuch as may concerne the inward governing and reglement of the ſoul, or affect the conſcience with remorſe and guiltineſſe: for firſt, we finde in ſeverall other texts, that if the difference be between Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, and the powers on earth, <hi>It is better to they God then man;</hi> and <note place="margin">Act. 5. 29.</note> that <hi>Paul</hi> meant no leſſe, appears clearly in the ſame Chaper, where he ſayes <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Ye muſt needs be ſubject, not only for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake,</hi> which cannot poſſibly ſucceed, if they commanded any thing contrary in conſcience, or the divine Supremacy, unto which only as it is acknowledged even by the light of Nature the conſcience is primarily ſubject, and not unto any other Law or Court, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe warrant and diſpenſation. Secondly, though we muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto all Powers, becauſe <hi>the Powers and Miniſters are of God,</hi> yet we are not bound to be ſubject to any of them, farther then their known reſpective powers extend, for the power which is aſſumed beyond their bounds is not of God, and ſo the reaſon which <hi>Paul</hi> urges, why we muſt be obedient falls to ground, I meane in reſpect of active obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and for paſſive eſpecially towards thoſe that are ſupreme, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Reader to ſuch as have ſo lately argued it ſo largely.</p>
            <p>I de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e not to ſeem as thinking that Chriſtians may live as they liſt, for when <hi>Paul</hi> told the Galatians, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 13. that they were called un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to liberty, he bid them withall, not uſe it for an occaſion to the fleſh; of that government is ever a whit the leſſe neceſſary in any Church, State, on Common-wealth, for even a Corporation, or family cannot well ſubſiſt without it: but it may not be imagined, that God did not preſcribe and leave expreſſe warrant, how he would have his owne houſe governed. <hi>Paul</hi> tells <hi>Timothy</hi> that he wrote thoſe things unto him, hoping to come in perſon ſhortly, but <hi>in caſe he carried longer that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:117052:28"/>
Timothy might know how he ought to behave himſelfe in the houſe of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 14. and as <hi>Paul</hi> thought theſe directions enough, and <hi>Timothy</hi> might not goe beyond commiſſion, ſo neither may we imploy any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, or inſtruments to uphold Chriſts government or houſhold; then ſuch as were by him preſcribed, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4, 5. are only <hi>Spirituall, but mighty through God to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds, caſting downe imaginations, and every high thing which exalteth is ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt:</hi> And he ſaid to the Epheſians, <hi>Put on the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God that you may be able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the divell, for we wreſtle not againſt fleſh and bloud, but againſt the rulers of darkneſſe of this world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſe in high places, Eph.</hi> 6. 11, 12. The armour preſcribed by him was only ſpirituall, and therefore their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies cannot be imagined otherwiſe then ſpirituall. But if civill pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or others, have authority in matters of Religion, then their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and Laws in that reſpect, muſt be as abſolute, as in any other, and ought equally to be obeyed, which would ingage the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſtill to the Diſcipline of the Common-Brayer-Book, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Epiſcopacy which for the preſent ſtand eſtabliſhed by ſundry Acts of Parliament unrepealed; and all Puritans, Non-conformiſts or Proteſtant ſeparatiſts of what ſort ſoever, are as ſubject to perſecution as any Papiſts, which appears by the reſpective Acts themſelves in that behalfe, 2. and 3. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. cap. 5. and 6. <hi>Edw</hi> 6. cap. 1. 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 2. And if Subjects may ſay that Epiſcopacie and the Service-Booke are Antichriſtian, contrary to the word of God, and may be their own judges in that reſpect, what hinders but they may ſay ſo too concerning Presbytery, or any other government? Wherefore there remaines no <hi>modium,</hi> either a Liberty of Conſcience muſt be permitted us to enjoy our owne opinions in matters of Religion, or elſe there is a neceſſity of being liable and ſubject againſt Conſcience, whenſoever the civill powers which ſurely are no more infallible then Eccleſiaſticall, ſhall happen to enact or ſtabliſh any thing elſe, leſſe conſonant and agreeing to the word of God.</p>
            <p>And whereas the 15. Chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> is commonly alledged, from whence they deduce the authority and uſe of Synods, with a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie of power in matters Eccleſiaſticall, I ſay that whatſoever is pretended from thence in behalfe of Synods, Papiſts have long ſince ſaid the ſame, and far more in favour of their Generall Councells, but that there is no ground at all in that place, neither for Synods, or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councells, in that way which is pretended by either of them, beſides ſundry others, will manifeſtly appeare by theſe few reaſons:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117052:28"/>
Firſt, becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> with the others ſent from <hi>Antioch,</hi> did not appeare as Commiſſioners or Repreſentatives at the conſultation of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> jointly to conſult with the <hi>Apoſtles and Elders</hi> about the <note place="margin">Act. 15. 4. 5.</note> matter in queſtion, but only made relation of their meſſage, as bare meſſengers. 2. The Text it ſelfe ſaies, they ſhould go to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> unto the <hi>Apoſtles and Elders</hi> about this queſtion, and not unto a Synod. <note place="margin">Verſ. 2.</note> Thirdly, the Apoſtles and Elders of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> only, came together to conſider of the buſineſſe, as appeares by collating verſ. 6. with verſ. 2. and 4. the multitude which were then preſent, being perhaps ſtanders <note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> by, as I may ſo ſay, or rather the Brethren alſo, who if they did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult in v. 23. they were the Brethren of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the naming whereof evidences more plainly, that there were no others who conſulted. Fourthly, <hi>Synia</hi> and <hi>Cilicia</hi> had no Commiſſioners there, for if they had, they would have been named as well as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> when the <hi>Apoſtles, Elders and Brethren of Jeruſalem wrote their letters,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree <note place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> ſhould have been publiſhed in the name of the Commiſſioners, and Repreſentatives of <hi>Antioch, Syria, Cilicia,</hi> and all others that did conſult, as well as of the Apoſtles, Elders, and Brethren of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> had they been all aſſembled in a Synod, and ſo much more would it have obliged their reſpective Churches, whom they repreſented: But perhaps it may be not improbably conjectured that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> as they paſſed from <hi>Antioch</hi> through <hi>Cilicia</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> underſtanding that the Churches there were no leſſe diſquieted with the ſame falſe doctrines, of their own accords informed the Apoſtles, Elders and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſo much at ſome more private ſeaſon, whereupon they joyned them together in their Chriſtian care, and directed their letters joyntly to all the Gentiles of <hi>Antioch, Syria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia,</hi> becauſe it was equally available to them all, though the queſtion was only mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by thoſe of <hi>Antioch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Fifthly, the Apoſtles and Elders anſwer of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> does not imply any neceſſity of thoſe other Churches ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion unto their determination, otherwiſe then infallibly inſpired men, as appears by ver. 28. Sixtly, the reſult of the Aſſembly, was not publiſhed, nor the letters wrote as from a Synod, but in the name of <hi>the Church of Jeruſalem to the Churches of Antioch, Syria and Cilicia,</hi> for it ſaies verſ. 22. It pleaſed <hi>the Apoſtles and Elders with the whole Church</hi> to ſend choſen men, &amp;c. and verſ. 23. The Apoſtles and Elders and Brethren ſend greeting, whereas had they been aſſembled in Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calibus or as a Synod, they would never have termed themſelves by the denomination of a Church: And ſeventhly, they impoſed not their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees with <hi>Anathema's,</hi> or upon the Churches utmoſt perill of fire and ſword, beſides whatſoever was then decreed by that pretended Synod,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117052:29"/>
was only that Chriſtians ſhould abſtaine from means offered unto Idols, <note place="margin">Verſ. 29.</note> from bloud, things ſtrangled and from fornication, with an expreſſe preamble, That it ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and them not lay <note place="margin">Verſ. 28.</note> any greater burden then thoſe neceſſary thinge, but the meat offered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Idolls was quickly diſpenced with, and for bloud and things ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 8. and 10. Chap.</note> we take liberty unto our ſelves; but if Synods and civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates would raiſe no further impoſitions, for matters of Religion, nor impoſe other penalties then are there ſpecified, it would not be ſo bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome, or ſo ſlaviſh a bondage to Gods Saints, and moſt conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Chriſtians, as they have been faine to prevent by flight, or live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to the great vexation of their ſoules, and perhaps not altogether without a doubting conſcience.</p>
            <p>But why doe not Synods begin all their decrees, with, <hi>It pleaſeth the Holy Ghoſt and us?</hi> &amp;c. this me thinks is more plauſible and eaſier to be beleeved, then the forcing of their decrees and votes upon others can be digeſted; for if any man tell me, he is ſometime miraculouſly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I have no infallible means to diſprove him, though it were falſe, and ſometimes I may ſee juſt inducements to beleeve him, but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly beleeve what he propounds unto me, contrary to mine owne reaſon and underſtanding: and yet though the Apoſtles, Elders, and Church of Chriſt in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> were immediately inſpired, and ſpake in the Holy Ghoſts name, yet they fixed not to their decrees any other conjuration or threatnings, then, <hi>If you doe theſe things, you ſhall doe well.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act 15. 29</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory Nazienzen</hi> could ſay that he never ſaw good end of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councells; and <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> in theſe latter times, both eminent <note place="margin">Nazienz. ad Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>co. Epiſt. 55. Grotii A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. cap. 6. p. 108.</note> for learning, and a friend to the Church Government of the united Provinces, does notwithſtanding affirm, that he could never underſtand how Synods can prove a ſingular remedy for reconciling differences in Religion: and indeed as it may eaſily be obſerved, that Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells and Synods, have ſeldome had good ſucceſſe, ſo for the moſt part, it may eaſily appeare, that there could not much better be expected, for commonly the choice of ſuch as were ſent thither, was factious or ſiding at the leaſt, and the whole proceedings accordingly, they ſought rather to decide matters by a major part of voyces, then by mature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating and arguing of the queſtion, they did take advantages as well for alledging their owne reaſons, as concealing, or over-ſhadowing the reaſons of ſuch as were of contrary opinions, that they might not be heard, debated, or throughly underſtood, and being in all reſpects watchfull, how they might with craft and ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ty circumvent, and over reach one another, to compaſſe their private intereſts, or indirect ends,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117052:29"/>
which the reſpective parties that ſent them thither did principally aime at, amongſt other ſtratagems and pollicies, it hath not been the leaſt to lay hold of ſuch times and ſeaſons, to make their motions or forbeare, when ſuch, or ſuch were preſent or abſent, which might beſt further or hinder, by ſeconding or contradicting of their arguments.</p>
            <p>But by Hiſtories and Records of what paſſed betwixt all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Nations almoſt, ſince the Reformation, it appears plainly, that though in ſome Countries, and at ſome times, when certaine hot ſpirits were predominant, there hath been for a ſpirit, very bitter perſecuting of Proteſtants for difference in Religion, yet their opinions and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions when confiderately reſolved were ſtill ſettled for Liberty of Conſcience; and <hi>Calvin</hi> tells us, That the holy Biſhops [of ancient <note place="margin">Inſtit. lib. 4. cap. 11. ſect. 3.</note> times] did not exerciſe their authority in fining, impriſoning, and civill puniſhments, and for his owne judgement in this particular, he ſaies, Though he write a whole tract about puniſhing of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, <note place="margin">Ibid. ſect. 16.</note> yet he could not chuſe but acknowledge ſo much truth in a few lines only as confutes the whole Treatiſe, where he tells us, That as the Church hath no power of forcing of its owne, ſo neither may it require ſuch of civill Magiſtrates, to imploy it in a coercive way: And <hi>Beza,</hi> God never gave power to man for impoſing Lawes upon the Conſcience, nor can endure that any body beſides himſelfe ſhould beare ſway or dominion over the mindes of men, <hi>de Haeret. à Civil. Magiſt. puniendis.</hi> The States of the united Provinces, when they firſt began to free themſelves from the Spaniſh tyranny, declared, That <hi>they took not up Armes for matter of Religion,</hi> as appears by letters which the States of <hi>Holland</hi> at that time wrote unto thoſe of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> in his Apologie, of thoſe that governed Holland, <note place="margin">Cap. 2. p. 24.</note> and the neighbouring Nations in 1618. for then <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall other chiefe Townes were abſolutely Popiſh for matter of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and yet all thoſe Provinces and ſeverall Townes did unammouſly agree, that, though they joyned their force againſt the Spaniard and common enemy, for redemption and maintenance of their priviledges and immunities, yet the liberty and freedome of Conſcience ſhould be reſerved to all, and each of them reſpectively: The Proteſtants of <hi>Switzerland</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> have publiſhed to the ſame purpoſe in their Confeſſions and Manifeſto's, and even of latter yeares, when the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of Dort was firſt thought on to be aſſembled, moſt of the States and Townes declared themſelves before hand, that it was not their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that the ſaid Synod ſhould oblige them unto any thing that was not agreeable to their laws and government, which, as I ſaid before, had abundantly eſtabliſhed and ratified a Liberty of Conſcience to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117052:30"/>
every particular perſon that inhabited amongſt them: And though upon the determination of the ſame Synod, in the point of Predeſtination a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Arminians, there enſued ſuddenly in ſome few places by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of a moſt violent party, ſeconded by the Prince, a fierce per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and baniſhment of divers Miniſters and others which were of that opinion, with a totall ſilencing and inhibiting them to preach, yet they were quickly reſtored againe, and have now their places of publicke meetings, and greater liberty then ever, and that in Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam and Utreckt, where they had ſuffered moſt, to the very change and alteration of their government, as may be ſeen more at large in <hi>Grotius</hi> his Apologie: But the States of Friſia in July 1622. put out a ſevere edict which is to be ſeen in Print, that none of the Dort Synod decrees ſhould be put in execution throughout their juriſdiction, untill they were by themſelves, in their owne Courts and Magiſtrates approved on; and in fine, I doe not finde ſo much as any one place, or City throughout the united Provinces, where any one decree which that Synod paſſed, is at preſent coercively enforced upon the inhabitants in any kinde; but contrary wiſe it is well knowne to all, how they permit people of all Religions to live amongſt them, and though they have continuall wars with Spain, and Papiſts in ſome Towns amongſt them have more liberty then in others, yet every where their freedome is great, and though in ſome places they are one fourth or one halfe part Papiſts, yet doe not the States ſubject themſelves to be terrified or troubled with jealouſies or other plots and treacheries then in puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the authours at ſuch times as they happen to be diſcovered; I wiſh it were well weighed, whether the great liberty and freedome of the Goſpel which they permit, <hi>That Chriſt be preached whether through contention or of good will,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> deſired, and rejoyced at, may <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 18.</note> not be a great meanes to prevaile with God Almighty thus to proſper them although they may otherwiſe have failings and weakneſſes, which worldly and carnall policies are moſt apt to bee overtaken with.</p>
            <p>If the whole manner of Gods worſhip were revealed unto us, or any State or Church, and that ſuch a Church or State could be certaine to be in the preſent poſſeſſion, and practiſe of the whole truth, without any mixture of ſuperſtition and Idolatry, then would there be far more colour and ground for erecting an Inquiſition Office, or Spirituall Court to bring a Nation, a Countrey, or all Chriſtendome unto a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity both of Diſcipline and Doctrine, but this appeares plainly to be otherwiſe in both reſpects: Firſt, no Church can poſſibly be ſure to be without a mixture of errour and ſuperſtition, in that <hi>it is neceſſary
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117052:30"/>
there ſhould be herefies,</hi> that they which are approved might be made <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 19. Matth. 24. 24. 2 Pet. 2. 1. 1 Joh. 4. 1. 1 Tim. 4. 1</note> manifeſt, and beſides we are foretold that there ſhall be <hi>falſe Chriſts</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> and for that cauſe we are commanded to <hi>trie the Spirits whether they be of God or no:</hi> Then ſecondly, God is pleaſed only to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Goſpel to us by peecemeals, as we become worthy and capable of the myſteries and truth thereof, which our Saviour teſtifies in <hi>John, John 16. 12, 13. I have yet many things to ſay unto you, but you cannot beare them now,</hi> howbeit when the Spirit of truth is come, He will guide you into <hi>all truth:</hi> Now though the Spirit which is the Holy Ghoſt be <note place="margin">Math. 28. 20.</note> come, and is with his Saints unto the end of the world, teaching and inſtructing them in ſo many wholeſome truths, as are ſufficient for their ſalvation, yet moſt evident it is that God ſtill diſcovers <hi>new truths</hi> or <hi>a greater meaſure of the ſame truths</hi> by obedience, unto which he intends to bring unto ſalvation ſuch as are then living, or to be borne hereafter; and this appeares further from St. <hi>Pauls</hi> words to the Corinthians, where he ſaies, <hi>We know but in part,</hi> and <hi>when I was a childe I ſpake as a childe,</hi> underſtood and thought as a childe, but <hi>when I became a man, I put away childiſh things, 1 Cor. 13. 9. 11. Strong meat belongeth to men that are of a full age, Heb.</hi> 5. 13. In another place, <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> And <hi>I have fed you with milke and not with meat, for hitherto yee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16. 1 Cor. 3. 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>were not able to beare it, neither yet are ye able, for ye are yet carnall:</hi> And of himſelfe though he were extraordinary and miraculouſly gifted out of a ſanctified zeale magnifying himſelfe unto the Philipians, he ſaies, <hi>Not as though I were already perfect,</hi> but forgetting theſe things which are behinde, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaching forth unto thoſe things which are before, <hi>I preſſe towards the marke,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 13. 12, 13, 14. Beſides, if all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were equally enlightned, and had the ſame meaſure and ſtrength of faith and knowledge, it would have been needleſſe for the Apoſtle to exhort as to <hi>beare with one another,</hi> there would have been no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for <hi>ſuch as are ſtrong to comport the weak,</hi> not all in generall to <hi>bear one anothers burden,</hi> which is required of us as the <hi>fulfilling of the Law of Chriſt, Rom. 15. 1. Gal.</hi> 6. 2. But the ſame cauſe which made the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians incapable of meat, ſuch further truths and myſteries as St. <hi>Paul</hi> had to diſcover unto them, reſides in us doubtleſſe, and that in as great a meaſure, which is carnality, and conſequently witholds Gods Spirit from revealing a great part of his bleſſed will unto us, otherwiſe then as we grow leſſe carnally minded, and more ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>And whereas it will be ſaid by ſome, that they have all the principalls <note place="margin">Object.</note> and fundamentalls of Religion revealed unto them, whereby they may be wiſe unto ſalvation, which is as much as they are obliged to, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no more: I crave leave to anſwer ſuch with another queſtion or <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:117052:31"/>
two, and aske, Doe you not ſometimes pray, <hi>that Gods will may be done</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth 6. 10. and 5 48. Phil. 2. 5. Eph 4. 13.</note> 
               <hi>on earth, as it is in heaven?</hi> And are you qualified to do your part thereof? Are you <hi>perfect as your heavenly Father is perfect? Is the ſame minde in you which is in Chriſt Jeſus?</hi> Unleſſe you have attained to this perfection, according to the meaſure and fulneſſe of Chriſt Jeſus, there is yet a part, which unleſſe you uſe all poſſible meanes to arrive to, though I cannot tell you when, or whether you ſhall or no, I ſee no ground whereby you may be ſure, as yet, to have that full proportion, either of truth or knowledge, which you ought to have; much leſſe how you can reaſonably excuſe the obſtructing, as much as in youlyes, the free paſſage of the Goſpell, the limiting and ſtinting of all ſpirituall gifts, with the quenching of Gods bleſſed Spirit, all which are ſent for the farther inſtruction and illumination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> tells the ſame Corinthians, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. That <hi>the naturall man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God,</hi> for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him, neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned: And our Saviour told <hi>Peter, Matth.</hi> 16. 17 That <hi>fleſh and bloud had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it unto him, but his Father which was in heaven:</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them to <hi>grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18. All which are undeniable arguments, that though a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian live never ſo long, yet he both may, and ought ſtill to <hi>grow from grace to grace, and from knowledge to knowledge,</hi> continually ayming, <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 13.</note> and endeavouring, untill he arrive to a perfect man <hi>according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſtature and fulneſſe of Chriſt,</hi> in both which reſpects an inquiſition or perſecution for matters of Religion may not be tollerated: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it would as much as in us lyes, ſtill withold ſuch ſaving truth and knowledge as yet undiſcovered, and unto which we are to attaine by degrees only, for not any of them but at firſt ſight and hearing, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted hereſie to moſt men, and much adoe there is before we will imbrace it: And ſecondly, in that perſecution for Religion, would render us altogether incapable of ever purging and reforming our ſelves from ſuch erronious doctrines and ſuperſtitions, as are amongſt us for the preſent, and what would this be otherwiſe then a <hi>meer forme of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof,</hi> from which <hi>Timothy</hi> was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to turne away? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. 7. But as was ſaid before, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 48. our Saviour commands us to be <hi>perfect even as our heavenly Father is perfect;</hi> and in that forme of prayer which he taught us, cap. 6. 10. we were ordered to make requeſt, <hi>That Gods will may be done in earth as it is in heaven,</hi> unto which height of godlineſſe we may be ſure not to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, being ſtill ſo much further off, as we apprehend our ſelves to have attained it, forbearing to preſſe forwads, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117052:31"/>
Philipians, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 14. 15. <hi>I preſſe towards the marke</hi> for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus: let us therefore <hi>as many as be perfect be thus minded, and if in any thing you be otherwiſe minded God ſhall reveale even this unto you:</hi> And S. <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle generall, exhorts thoſe <note place="margin">Cap. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note> Chriſtians, <hi>As new borne babes to deſire the ſincere milke of the word that they may grow thereby,</hi> not that they ſhould thinke themſelves to have attained either unto a perfection and fulneſſe of knowledge, or purity of profeſſion, both which muſt be ſuppoſed, or elſe the ground-worke <note place="margin">Note.</note> and foundation whereon they build their Inquiſition houſe for ſetling a uniformity, is ſo much more unwarrantable and unſound.</p>
            <p>The Parable of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 29, 30. wherein he forbids the pulling up the tares leſt they pull up the good wheat with them, and commands, <hi>That both tares and wheat be let grow together till harveſt,</hi> ſeems to me a full argument that the State ſhould not be forwards in putting any to death, ſave ſuch as are expreſſely warranted by the word of God, but this place makes eſpecially againſt perſecution for matters of Religion; for though every body can diſtinguiſh tares from corne, yet it is not ſo with hereſies and errours in point of Doctrine; beſides, the outward man may ſo conforme himſelfe if he will, as that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the world to finde him out, becauſe they cannot arrive to the heart, and what ever externall meanes may be uſed, they worke only upon the body, and cannot reach the ſoule: But perſecution for Religion does not only contradict the Scripture, but is contrary to common ſenſe and reaſon, as will appeare if you conſider, that, although we ſay proverbially, <hi>facile credimus, quod libenter volumus;</hi> yet a man of himſelfe cannot poſſibly beleeve what he himſelfe deſires to beleeve, before his judgement and underſtanding be convinced, ſo that unleſſe it be a good argument, to prevaile upon a mans judgement and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to ſay, beleeve this or that point of doctrine upon penalty of loſing your ears, or the like, it muſt needs be extravagant and unjuſt to practiſe it: let us not then goe againſt our owne reaſon, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture where it is ſaid, That <hi>though Paul plant, and Apollo water, it is God that gives encreaſe:</hi> And our Saviour tells us, That <hi>no man can come to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 6 Joh. 6. 44. 63. 65.</note> 
               <hi>him except the Father draw him,</hi> that it is <hi>the Spirit which quickneth,</hi> and that <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fleſh profiteth nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is yet another place of Scripture which ſpeakes more plainly, letting all Inquiſitors and Perſecutors know, that though they had the ſpirit of divination and diſcerning, wherewith they could be certaine to have diſcovered ſuch as preach the Goſpell out of ſtrife and envie, and not ſincerely, yet they are not to ſilence them, but be glad that the Goſpel be preached in a weake and erronious manner, then not at all,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117052:32"/>
for even as a man that holds faſt with his hands, if his feet ſlip, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover himſelfe againe, ſo if Chriſt the foundation be kept, though for the preſent they may preach and teach many a falſe doctrine, yet wee may be certaine that all rotten unſound ſuperſtructures and erronious tenets ſhall fall downe in Gods good time and ſeaſon, whileſt the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation remaines ſure for ever: <hi>He that hath given us Chriſt, will with him,</hi> but at his owne good pleaſure <hi>give us all things; Paul</hi> thought this was a good argument, and ſo far bare with all mens infirmities, that as <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 32</note> he ſayes of himſelfe to the end he might have opportunity to preach the Goſpel, <hi>he became all things to all men, that by all meanes he might ſave</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 9. 20, 21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>ſome,</hi> unto the Jews as a Jew that he might gaine the Jews, to them that are under the Law, as under the Law, and to them that were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Law, as without Law, that he might gaine both; and leſt you might thinke him a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertine in all this, and without Law to God, he tells you he was all this while <hi>under the Law to Chriſt,</hi> and doubtleſſe did him no ſmall ſervice in thus complying: But that you may gueſſe in what manner and how far forth he had been indulgent at ſuch other times, the relation whereof we doe not finde recorded, take what he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unto the Philippians. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 16. 17. 18, 19. <hi>Some preach Chriſt even of envy and ſtrife,</hi> and <hi>ſome alſo upon good will,</hi> the one preach Chriſt of <hi>contention, not ſincerely,</hi> ſuppoſing to adde affliction to my bonds, but the other of <hi>love,</hi> knowing that I am ſet for the defence of the Goſpel: what then? <hi>notwithſtanding every way, whether in pretence, or in truth, Chriſt is preached, and I therein doe rejoyce, yea and will rejoyce,</hi> for I know that this ſhall turne to my ſalvation through your prayers, and the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Yea will ſome ſay great ſhame it were if we ſhould not rejoyce that Chriſt be truly preached in what manner ſoever; but ſuch as we ſilence and perſecute though they confeſſe and preach Chriſt in words, yet they hold certaine erronious tenets which ſtrike at the foundation, and overthrow Chriſtianity: I deſire ſuch to remember thoſe Scriptures which ſay, that, <hi>Whoſoever is borne of God doth not commit ſin,</hi> for his ſeed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin becauſe he is borne of God: <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Joh. 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>beleeveth in him ſhall not periſh but have eternall life: And whoſoever ſhall confeſſe that Jeſus is the Sonne of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John. 3 13 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 4 15</note> 
               <hi>God:</hi> Now as we know that <hi>David</hi> though he committed adultery and murder, was borne of God notwithſtanding this text, becauſe it means only that God imputes not ſinne unto them that are borne of God; ſo he that beleeveth in God, and confeſſeth that Jeſus is the Son of God, though he do together with this foundation, hold certain points which may ſeem to croſſe it, and be in a great degree erronious, but contrary
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117052:32"/>
to his owne intention, it is both very poſſible and probable, that ſuch a one notwithſtanding ſhall not periſh, but God dwelleth in him, and he in God.</p>
            <p>In the very Bible we finde ſeverall texts and paſſages which ſeem to thwait and contradict themſelves, yet we are certaine, that the whole Scripture being the inſpiration of one, and the ſame bleſſed Spirit, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be at unity within it ſelfe, and all good Chriſtians are fully aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereof, though they be not able ſometimes to make it appeare ſo to their weake and carnall underſtandings; and in ſuch caſes we have the example of St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 11. 13. the great <hi>Apoſtle of the Gentiles,</hi> who though he teſtified of himſelfe, that he gave his judgement <hi>as one</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 25. 40.</note> 
               <hi>that had obtained mercy of the Lord to be faithfull, and thought that he alſo had the Spirit of God,</hi> yet having waded into the myſtery of Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſo far as his owne reaſon could arive, burſt out into a moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout admiration, <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdome and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 33.</note> 
               <hi>of God, how unſearchable are his judgements, and his wayes paſt fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the Romans, chap. 3. 28. it is ſaid, Therefore we conclude that a <hi>man is juſtified by faith without the deeds of the Law:</hi> And St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>James</hi> 2. 24. Ye ſee then how that <hi>by workes a man is juſtified, and not by faith only:</hi> Now as we are fully aſſured that theſe two Scriptures though they differ ſo much litterally, are notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding not only in their owne being reconcileable, but even in our ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low capacities and apprehenſions: And as God had good cauſe why he counted <hi>Paul faithfull</hi> and <hi>put him into the Miniſtery, who was before</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>a blaſphemer and perſecuter:</hi> So we may ſafely thinke, that God can much more (after the manner of men be it ſpoken) tell how to proſper their endeavours, and bring unto ſalvation, <hi>ſuch as beleeve in him, and confeſſe Jeſus to be the Son of God,</hi> for his word and promiſe are engaged and cannot be fruſtrated through their weakneſſes and unſoundneſſe in ſome points of Diſcipline, Doctrine, or of both: But it will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, <note place="margin">Object.</note> why ſhould ſuch be ſuffered to preach Chriſt, who withall mix unſound doctrine, ſince there may be teachers enough beſides, who are all orthodox and unqueſtionable? I anſwer, That this is not the true ſtate of the caſe, for that the Puritans or other conſcientious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> hold their owne teachers to be the ſoundeſt, and if they be ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, conceive they are bound, without power of diſpencing with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to heare none at all, rather then ſuch with whom they cannot poſſibly joyne or be preſent without <hi>a doubting and condemning conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 23. Matth. 13. 29, 30.</note> ſo that at the very beſt this can be but <hi>a pulling up of good wheat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the tares,</hi> which as was ſaid before, our Saviour would not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117052:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:117052:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:117052:34"/>
have ſo much as hazarded and endangered; or <hi>a doing evill that good</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>may come of it, which is as abſolutely forbidden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will therefore forbeare to make any further application of <hi>Pauls</hi> rejoycing ſo Chriſt were preached in whatſoever manner, but beſeech with meekneſſe all ſuch as read it, to pauſe a little and conſider, that ſince <hi>Paul</hi> rejoyced in whatſoever way that Chriſt was preached, <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of contention, envy, pretence, or in truth,</hi> how inexcuſable will all thoſe be that perſecute or ſilence ſuch as preach him in any other maner then they themſelves preſcribe, whereby many eminent abilities and gifts have been ſmothered and loſt: To the ſame purpoſe is that place in St. <hi>Markes</hi> Goſpel, where <hi>John</hi> in the name of the Apoſtles tells our Saviour, ſaying, Maſter, we ſaw one caſting out divells in thy name, and he followeth not us, and <hi>We forbad him becauſe he followeth not us,</hi> but Jeſus ſaid, <hi>forbid him not, for there is no man which ſhall doe a miracle in my name that can lightly ſpeake evill of me,</hi> he that is not againſt us, is on our part, <hi>Marke</hi> 9. 38, 39, 40.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> tells the Hebrewes, how <hi>He that deſpiſed Moſes law dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy under two or three witneſſes;</hi> and askes them, <hi>how much ſorer pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 28, 29.</note> 
               <hi>they ſuppoſed ſuch ſhould be thought worthy of, who have trodden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot the Son of God,</hi> and counted the bloud of the Covenant where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was ſanctified, an unholy thing, which is a plain evidence, that though ſuch as live under the Goſpel, and neglect or deſpiſe the means of comming to the knowledge, or yet ſpeake againſt the truth thereof, deſerve greater puniſhment then thoſe that violated the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which was certaine death in the mouth of two or three witneſſes, yet he ſaies not that it ought to be ſo under the Goſpel; but though he ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate the crime as far more heynous under the Goſpel, yet he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines to ſay they ſhould be puniſhed corporally in this life, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſinuates that it muſt be left untill the day of judgement, as appeares by the coherence with the words which follow, where he brings the Lord in, ſaying, <hi>Vengeance is mine, and I will recompence it:</hi> and againe, <note place="margin">Ver. 30. 31.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord ſhall judge his people: It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God:</hi> And this is yet more manifeſt, if we conſider that there had been thouſands of thoſe which thus rejected and violated the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel which then had not been puniſhed with death according to the <note place="margin">Note.</note> law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and yet <hi>Paul</hi> for all this did not blame thoſe Chriſtians for omitting to doe corporall execution on them, or leave any order that the civill Magiſtrate ſhould afterwards have ſuch power when they became Chriſtian: And if <hi>Paul</hi> tells <hi>Titus</hi> that a Biſhop muſt not be ſoone angry, nor a ſtriker; and <hi>Peter</hi> bids the Elders take the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 7. 1 Pet. 5. 2, 3.</note> of Gods flocke, not being Lords over Gods heritage, but as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117052:34"/>
to the flocke; how ſhall a Presbyter that is a ſtriker, or that Lords it over the flocke of Chriſt be juſtified? or how can he be ſaid to be leſſe then a ſtriker, that paſſes ſentence of condemnation to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, impriſonment, and death, or not to Lord it over the flock of Chriſt, that impoſes laws upon their conſciences?</p>
            <p>But did theſe perſecuters of God and good men conſider, that to be perſecuted, is a mark and ſigne of the true Church, and conſequently to perſecute, an infallible character of unſound Chriſtians and the Church malignant, in charity we ought to thinke they might likely be reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, I ſhall therefore intreat them for their owne direction to call to minde, what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the Galathians, <hi>viz.</hi> Now <hi>we, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 28, 29.</note> 
               <hi>as Iſaac was, are the children of promiſe,</hi> but <hi>as then he that was borne after the fleſh perſecuted him that was borne after the Spirit, even ſo it is now:</hi> This text declares how the true Church and true Beleevers are children of the promiſe, figured out in <hi>Abel, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> perſecuted by <hi>Cain,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 8. cap. 16. 11 12. cap. 17. 41.</note> 
               <hi>Iſmael, Eſau,</hi> and their poſterity, children of the bond-woman, teaching us in expreſſe words, that as thoſe which perſecuted in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were not the Elect or children of the promiſe, ſo now the beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God were perſecuted under the Goſpel; which will yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare more plainly to ſuch as have their underſtanding darkned, if they reflect likewiſe upon theſe other Scriptures: <hi>He that loveth not his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not of God,</hi> for this is the meſſage that we heard from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 10, 11, 12.</note> that we ſhould love one another, <hi>not as Cain, who was of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked one, and ſlew his brother: and wherefore ſlew he him? becauſe his works were evill, and his brothers righteous:</hi> And our Saviour told his Diſciples, <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 16. Joh. 16. 20.</note> 
               <hi>I ſend you as ſheep in the midſt of wolves; ye ſhall weep and lament, but the world ſhall rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the practiſe of perſecution for difference in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion were a ſigne of the true Church, then that Church were likelieſt to be the trueſt Church that did moſt perſecute others, which I beleeve <note place="margin">Note.</note> will be denied by all Proteſtants, or elſe they muſt condemne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in ſuffering the Papiſts to go beyond them in perſecuting others: and ſecondly, if perſecution were a note of the true Church, it would inſtigate and encourage all States and Churches to double and encreaſe their perſecutions, untill each of them had attained to the moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite degrees and height of cruelty and tyranny.</p>
            <p>Againe, though perſecution for conſcience ſake be never ſo much practiſed, it is condemned by all men in every body but themſelves, for who is there that blames himſelf for perſecuting others, or who would be contented to be perſecuted himſelfe? and ſo far is perſecution from propagating of the Goſpel, that nothing in humane appearance can
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117052:35"/>
poſſibly hinder it ſo much, for the Papiſts having got the upper hand and greateſt portion of the Chriſtian world into their power by vigour of their perſecution, hinder the bleſſed Goſpel from being truly taught in the ſimplicity and purity thereof; and as it is well knowne, that the beſt Churches have been in errours, ſometimes <hi>able to digeſt milke only,</hi> not capable of ſtrong meat, ſo by the rules and principalls of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 2.</note> it were impoſſible to grow ſtronger, or come into the light of truth againe, becauſe that according to ſuch diſcipline, ſuch as teach any new truth, or but a further meaſure of former trut hs ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, as it happened unto <hi>Paul</hi> and the other Apoſtles and Diſciples, under the calumnie of ſedition, hereſie, blaſphemy, or innovation, for <note place="margin">Acts 6. 13 Acts 24. 5 14 <hi>Object.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe was reduced to ſay, I worſhip God after the manner which they call hereſie: And whereas ſome will object, that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the Primitive times were weake as being newly planted, but that Chriſtians now adaies have attained to a larger meaſure of ſtrength and knowledge in the truth, I dare not ſubſcribe thereunto, and for whatever failings, errours and falſe doctrines ſuch men ſhall prove to <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> have been found in the Churches of <hi>Rome, Corinth, Jeruſalem, Antioch, Epheſus, Galatia,</hi> or any of the reſt during the Apoſtles times, when through weakneſſe and carnality they were ſaid to have need of milke, it will full eaſily appeare, that, as the infallibility of the Apoſtles, their <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 2, 3. Heb. 5 12.</note> diverſity and preheminencie of gifts, and miracles which they wrought, were far more efficacious means then at any time were ſince enjoyed; ſo none of our Proteſtant Churches at preſent, eſpecially Nationall, but will juſtifie the Primitive, in our owne greater errours, both for Diſcipline and Doctrine: It is true that if liberty be given for men to to teach what they will, there will appeare more falſe Teachers then ever, yet it were better that many falſe doctrines were publiſhed, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially with a good intention and out of weakneſſe only, then that one ſound truth ſhould be forcibly ſmothered or wilfully concealed; and by the incongruities and abſurdities which accompany erroneous and unſound doctrines, the truth appears ſtill more glorious, and wins o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the love thereof.</p>
            <p>Neither is this complying with weake conſciences, or the tollerating of ſeverall opinions, any other ſort of Libertiniſme, then what <hi>Paul</hi> practiſed, when <hi>he ſuffered all things leſt he ſhould hinder the Goſpsl,</hi> and <note place="margin">1 Cor 9. 12 21. 22.</note> 
               <hi>was made all things to all, that he might ſave ſome,</hi> at which very time hee profeſſed himſelf notwithſtanding to live not without law to God, but under law to Chriſt: And <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, <hi>We muſt live as free,</hi> but <hi>not uſing our liberty for a cloak of maliciouſneſſe,</hi> but as the ſervants of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 16. And if you demand whether Hereticks then may not be reclaimed? <note place="margin">Object.</note>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:117052:35"/>
I anſwer, That you both may, and ought to endeavour their reclaiming, <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> not by compulſive courſes, but with brotherly and Chriſtian admonition and inſtructions, by evidence of Scripture in demonſtration of the Spirit, and ſuch other peaceable and quiet wayes as are warrantable by the Word of God: but for ſuch as ſay, we have tried all ſaire means, and <note place="margin">Reply. Anſw.</note> none but coercive will prevaile; if they had order to make uſe of them, how can they be ſure that forcible means would have better ſucceſſe? and how much more blameable are they that uſe them, when they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have commiſſion, nor aſſurance that they ſhall prevaile?</p>
            <p>Our Saviour told his Diſciples, That <hi>if they were of the world, the world</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 15. 19.</note> 
               <hi>would love his owne,</hi> but <hi>he had choſen them out of the world, and therefore the world hated them,</hi> and leſt this ſhould not prove a ſufficient item to them and us, St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us plainly, How <hi>all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 12.</note> 
               <hi>muſt ſuffer perſecution:</hi> whereto that we may be the better induced, our Saviour in his Sermon on the Mount, amongſt other bleſſings pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces this unto them, <hi>Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you and perſecute you,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 11. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhall ſay all manner of evill againſt you falſely for my ſake,</hi> rejoyce and be exceeding glad for great is your reward in heaven, for <hi>ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you:</hi> And leſt ſuch poor diſtreſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould be to ſeek, how to behave themſelves in ſo great a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſtreſſe, the bleſſed Spirit of God by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Romans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 14. Mat. 5. 44. Joh. 5. 16. &amp; 15. 20. 1 Cor. 4. 12</note> us, <hi>to bleſſe ſuch as perſecute us,</hi> ſo that in theſe and many other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we have the practiſe of perſecution given us as a ſign to know the Church malignant by; and to be perſecuted as a love token, and moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar livery of Jeſus Chriſt to diſtinguiſh true from falſe beleevers.</p>
            <p>And if it be objected, that then there muſt be no true Church amongſt Chriſtians, and that all of them doe perſecute one another more or leſſe, <note place="margin">Object.</note> it wil notwithſtanding follow, that ſuch Chriſtian States and Churches as <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> perſecute moſt, are moſt corrupted, and though I could hope for their ſakes which ſtill retaine it with leſſe rigour, that every ſmaller degree of perſecuting Chriſtians which differ from them in opinion, may not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch to be true Chriſtians, though imperfect and failing in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, yet my earneſt deſires are, that all ſuch as are cauſers, counſellours or inſtruments promoting, or not endeavouring and diſſwading perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will ſeriouſly conſider with themſelves, whether, the thus perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one another by Chriſtian Churches which differ in opinions, though it ſhould not hinder them from being true Churches, yet if it may not be found, at leaſt, an errour and exceeding great blemiſh in them all, even thoſe that uſe it ſeldomeſt and in milder manner, expreſſely forbidden in ſo many places of Scripture, and continually declamed againſt by the whole proceedings of our Bleſſed Saviour, his Apoſtles, and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117052:36"/>
and truly mortified Chriſtians, famous for greateſt piety and devotion in their reſpective generations.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>John</hi> ſaies, That <hi>light is come into the world, and men loved darkneſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19, 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>rather then light becauſe their deeds were evill,</hi> for every one that doth evill, hateth light, neither commeth to the light leſt his deeds ſhould be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but <hi>he that doth the truth commeth to the light,</hi> that his deeds may be made manifeſt, that they are wrought in God: Methinkes we may well reſemble the true profeſſours of Jeſus Chriſt, to thoſe that ſeek the light, that the truth which they teach may be made manifeſt; and contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſuch to be falſe prophets and hypocrites, that hate the light leſt their beloved errours and counterfeit doctrines ſhould be diſcovered, reproved and forſaken: Indeed many a man hath been over confident, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up his body to be burnt in a bad cauſe, but this ſhould make ſuch as have a good one, to gather ſo much more courage to themſelves, and not decline any lawfull triall or diſputation, whereby falſhood would be vanquiſhed, and the light of truth ſhine out, ſo much more amiable and bright, as before it had greater oppoſition.</p>
            <p>In the ordinary courſe of the world betwixt two which are at law to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, when either of them uſes meanes to prolong the ſuit, and prevent what poſſibly he can the comming to a judgement, may we not ſay, and that juſtly too, that ſuch a man hath a bad cauſe, or elſe that he hath not all his proofes and evidences in readineſſe, eſpecially if we ſuppoſe that he knew he had a Judge who both underſtood his cauſe fully, and would infallibly do him juſtice? ſurely the ſame may be ſaid and that more war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably concerning Religion, and differences in opinion about any point thereof.</p>
            <p>Confidence and boldneſſe prevaile ſometimes, and that not a little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in a bad cauſe, but never fail when they maintaine a good one; we may ſee it in the <hi>Acts</hi> that both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> with the cauſe of Jeſus <note place="margin">Act. 4. 13.</note> Chriſt ſped the better for their boldneſſe, which when the Scribes, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>Annas,</hi> and all high Prieſts kindred ſaw, and perceived that they were unlearned and ignorant men, they marvelled, and took knowledge that they had been with Jeſus, And beholding the man which was hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſtanding with them, <hi>they could ſay nothing againſt it;</hi> and how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully the cauſe proſpered hereupon appears in that fourth Chapter to the <hi>Acts,</hi> which is well worth reading out, and cannot by a heart truly ſanctified be paſſed over without great admiration: St. <hi>Paul</hi> confirmes it <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 12 Phil. 3. 19. 20. 25.</note> unto the Epheſians, ſaying, That <hi>through faith in Jeſus Chriſt we have bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and acceſſe with confidence:</hi> And to the Philippians he hath yet a fuller expreſſion, where he ſayes, I know according to my earneſt expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hope that <hi>in nothing I ſhall be aſhamed, but that with all boldneſſe, as
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117052:36"/>
alwaies, ſo now alſo Chriſt ſhall be magnified in my body,</hi> whether it be by life or death, and <hi>having this confidence I know that I ſhall abide and continue with you all,</hi> for your furtherance and joy of faith: Surely as all true Beleevers have the ſame good cauſe and Goſpel, ſo can they not poſſibly fare worſe if they had but ſuch a faith and confidence as <hi>Pauls</hi> was: Now <note place="margin">Jam. 2, 2</note> true and lively faith cannot be without works, and the moſt eminent and glorious worke of all, is to ſeek the propagation of it, in ſuch means and manner as are moſt warrantable, and likelieſt by the precept and preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of our only wiſe Saviour, and his bleſſed Apoſtles to prove ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: Oh, let us not then defer the practiſe of it any longer! doe we ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that errour ſhould vanquiſh truth? this is ſo vaine that no man will confeſſe ſo much, but for their full conviction if they were ſo conceited, let them take notice what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the Corinthians, <hi>We cannot do</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13 8.</note> 
               <hi>any thing againſt the truth but for the truth;</hi> we may plot, contrive and endeavour whatſoever our owne depraved natures will ſuggeſt us to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, but great is the power of truth, and it will prevaile at laſt: or doe we then feare that the true profeſſours may fall from their former ſtedfaſtneſſe? it is true that ſome which once made profeſſion of the truth may fall from that profeſſion, but ſuch, though they make profeſſion of the truth, yet were they never true profeſſours, as St. <hi>John</hi> ſaies in his firſt Epiſtle, <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us,</hi> for if they had <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 1</note> been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us, but they went out, that they might be made manifeſt, that they were not all of us: And doubtleſſe it were much to be deſired, and all juſtifiable meanes to be imployed, whereby hypocrites, and ſuch as are not true at heart, might be beſt moved to diſcover themſelves of their owne accord, for then the people of God might be kept from falling into many a ſin through their ill example, and avoid many a temporall judgement and affliction for holding fellowſhip and communion with them; but bleſſed be God this is the worſt that can befall them, neither divells nor the deepeſt wiles of wicked reprobates can poſſibly deceive the true Profeſſours Gods Elect. <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 24.</note> Our Saviour hath paſſed his word, That <hi>not one of theſe little ones ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, Mat.</hi> 18. 4. And my ſheep heare my voyce, and I know them, and they follow me, and I give unto them eternall life, and <hi>they ſhall never pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, neither ſhall any man pluck them out of my hand; John</hi> 10. 27, 28. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies, <hi>We are perſecuted, but not forſaken, caſt down, but not deſtroyed,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 9. And he told <hi>Timothy</hi> That <hi>the foundation of God ſtandeth ſure,</hi> having this ſeale, <hi>that the Lord knoweth them that are his,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
            <p>But ſince <hi>hereſies muſt needs be,</hi> though a woe betide the authours of <note place="margin">Cap. 1. 87</note> them, how much more may we well thinke ſhould there be a Liberty of Conſcience? ſince the authours inſtead of woe, may be certain of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:117052:37"/>
and nothing can more manifeſt the truth, when all ſuch as for feare of impriſoning, fining, corporall puniſhment, or any worldly prerogative had heretofore made profeſſion thereof, would now appear in their own colours, and follow the falſe calls of their more falſe teachers, leaving truth to herſelfe, and ſuch only as did imbrace her in true ſincerity of heart; and yet this is not all the benefit which would accrue hereby, the greateſt and beſt part is ſtill behinde; for as in the Primitive times, when Scribes, Phariſes, and all the learned Doctors both Jews and Gentiles, <note place="margin">Note.</note> diſputed and oppoſed the truth with more liberty and freedome, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came then much more famous and prevailing, untill the myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity undertooke the protecting of it by the Civill Sword, which if it were but ſheathed againe, and the Bleſſed Spirit, which bloweth where it liſteth, not reſiſted, we might even in theſe dayes with Gods aſſiſtance, <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 8.</note> expect to ſee victorious trophees, and multitudes of Chriſtians ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and redeemed out of <hi>Babylon</hi> to the ſpeedier downfall of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay that the learned and wiſeſt men have alwaies been and are ſtill of opinion, that it is no good policie to ſuffer ſo many ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <note place="margin">Object.</note> Religions to be publickly profeſſed in one and the ſame Kingdome and juriſdiction, becauſe that though many men may be able with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to defend their owne Religion, and others perhaps ſtedfaſt and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate enough in their opinions what ever they be, yet if contrary tenets may be debated freely, and made profeſſion of without controle, ſome numbers more or leſſe amongſt ſuch multitudes of people, either by importunity, worldly advantages, or in that their ignorance or little knowledge in ſpirituall matters, is not able to withſtand the arguments which are urged againſt them, muſt needs be ſeduced and led a way from the Religion eſtabliſhed by Law: Whereto I anſwer, That the advice <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> of wiſe and learned men if they be otherwiſe alſo as well qualified, is to be far preferred before that of ignorant and leſſe wiſe, but ſuch whoſe affections and carnall luſts are mortified, and whoſe guifts are ſanctified, theſe mens counſells ought to take place before the deepeſt Polititians of State, or grand Rabbies of the Law or Goſpel: worldly wiſdome and humane learning are both uſefull and expedient, when they concur with Scripture, not againſt it: It was the argument of the Jews againſt our Saviour and his Apoſtles, That <hi>the Scribes, Phariſes and great ones beleeved not on him;</hi> the Papiſts urged the like, that all the learned Doctors and <note place="margin">oh. 7. 48.</note> profoundeſt ſchollars throughout the Chriſtian world were of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion againſt <hi>Luther</hi> and the firſt Reformers, and although we all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of how little account and force this argument was then, yet is it now as much ſtood upon, and altogether as weakly grounded, even by the greateſt part of Reformed Churches, againſt ſuch as yet ſtrive for,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117052:37"/>
and endeavour only a further Reformation: ſurely if ſuch would but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of what low condition and meane eſtate the Apoſtles were, they <note place="margin">Act. 4. 13. Matth. 4. 18. 21.</note> would never think the worſe of truth, becauſe it was held out unto them by men of moſt inferiour ranke and quality, this would make ſuch as are Scripture wiſe to thinke the better of it, for who are likelieſt to have ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualll things diſcovered to them, then ſuch as are ſpirituall themſelves? and who likelieſt to be ſpirituall, then ſuch as are poore, baſe and abject both in the eyes of others and their owne opinions? Surely St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks plaine to this purpoſe when he ſaies, <hi>Not many wiſe men after the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 26, 27, 28.</note> 
               <hi>fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called;</hi> But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and God hath choſen the weak things of the world to confound the things which are mighty, and <hi>baſe things</hi> of the world, and <hi>things which are deſpiſed</hi> hath God choſen: And againe, <hi>where is the wiſe? where is the ſcribe? where is the diſputer</hi> of <note place="margin">Ver. 20.</note> the world? hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdome of this world? And to the Corinthians he gives a reaſon why God made uſe of men of ſuch low ranke and eſteem in the world, to be the chiefeſt inſtruments of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating the Goſpel, when he ſayes, <hi>We have this treaſure in earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, that the excellencie of the power may be of God, and not of us,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 7. And in another place he ſaies, Chriſt ſent me to preach the Goſpel, <hi>not with wiſdome of words,</hi> leſt the croſſe of Chriſt ſhould be made of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 17. If theſe paſſages of Scripture with ſundry others were ſeriouſly conſidered, by a minde prepared to ſubmit to Gods good will and pleaſure what ever it were, when it ſhould be diſcovered unto him, ſuch a ſoule would not be ſwayd, and led a way with any carnall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges or worldly circumſtances how plauſible ſoever, ſince all ſuch are but <hi>vanity and vexation of ſpirit,</hi> as the wiſe man aſſures us: evidence of <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1. 2. 14.</note> Scripture is that only which ought to be our guide in what we do or ſay, our ſupreame rule or touchſtone to make triall of what we heare or ſee, according whereunto if we proceed, whatſoever be alledged to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, we may cleerly finde, That <hi>perſecution for matters of Religion does plainly croſſe ſo many places of Scripture, murders ſo many of Gods Saints, and ſo much hinders the propagation of the Goſpel, as no other erronious tenet or he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie whatſoever: for if the Goſpel had but a free paſſage, and the true Profeſſours liberty to teach and publiſh it, this only as a ſovereigne remedy and counter poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, would prevaile againſt all hereſies, unleſſe you will grant that errour may poſſibly vanquiſh truth:</hi> and though our owne fond fancies ſhould ſuggeſt never ſo many inconveniences to enſue thereon, we ought to reſt ſatisfied with ſo great a manifeſtation of Gods revealed will, no waies attempting any thing, or cleaving to ſuch opinions, which either directly, or by ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſequence and induction may hinder the preaching of the Goſpel to all Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:117052:38"/>
If Kings or States may lawfully enact a Religion, or ſettle any point of faith to be beleeved and practiſed by force and virtue of a new law, then ought all ſubjects to be conformable thereunto, and ſo become ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to change and alter their Religion, ſo often as the State and chiefeſt Councell of the Land ſhall deem juſt and requiſite; for as our predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours could not make a law to binde their ſucceſſours irrevocably, or <note place="margin">Note.</note> longer then they pleaſed themſelves in civill matters, much leſſe in what concerns the Conſcience; ſo neither can we that are now living engage our poſterity in any act, but what they may repeal at pleaſure, with the ſame liberty and power by which it was made, ſince the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome being a body politicke indowed with a ſupremacie, cannot have greater or leſſe power over it ſelfe at one time then another; wherefore ſince it is our duty to think very reverently of Laws and Acts when once eſtabliſhed by the higheſt Court, yet if we conſider that they themſelves doe not aſſume infallibility, that both they, Synods, and chiefe Generall Councells have thought it expedient and juſt to repeal, alter, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times enact Laws, concerning Diſcipline and Doctrine quite contrary to their predeceſſours, by which means a people in their life time have been compelled to change Religion twice or thrice; my humbleſt deſires beg leave to proſtrate themſelves in meekneſſe and moſt ſubmiſſive manner unto the three eſtates in Parliament, That all former acts which counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance perſecution for matters of Religion may be repealed, and Liberty of Conſcience which is the greateſt liberty the Goſpel brings, reſtored, leſt whileſt the prevailing party of <hi>Proteſtants in England</hi> think it lawfull to force other Proteſtants, becauſe leſſe in number, and differing from them in opinion, to change Religion; God in juſtice permit Papiſts to doe the like with <hi>Proteſtants in Ireland,</hi> as well for our ſins as their owne, to the further deſolation of both Kingdomes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
